<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:prism="http://prismstandard.org/namespaces/basic/2.0/">
<channel>
<title>Head &amp; Neck Cancer – DOI-Enriched Feed</title>
<link>https://colmmemedsurv.github.io/sentinelnode/</link>
<description>Curated head &amp; neck cancer literature with DOI-based enrichment.</description>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2025 22:32:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
<item>
<title>Merkel-Cell Carcinoma</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1056/nejmicm2513302</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1056/nejmicm2513302</guid>
<pubDate>2025-12-18</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Zunaid Ahmed; Willem Visser</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>New England Journal of Medicine</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1056/NEJMicm2513302</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: New England Journal of Medicine | DOI: 10.1056/NEJMicm2513302</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>A 72-year-old woman presented with a 3.5-month history of an enlarging, painless lump on her cheek. Examination showed a dome-shaped, reddish nodule on the left cheek, with a shiny surface and central hemorrhagic crust.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>[Correspondence] Misclassification of p16-positive, HPV-negative patients biases de-escalation trials</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s1470-2045(25)00616-3</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1016/s1470-2045(25)00616-3</guid>
<pubDate>2025-12</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Jessica T Lovett; Michael T Wotman; Marshall Posner</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>The Lancet Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1016/S1470-2045(25)00616-3</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: The Lancet Oncology | DOI: 10.1016/S1470-2045(25)00616-3</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>We read with interest the Article by Daniel Ma and colleagues in The Lancet Oncology.1 Ma and colleagues should be congratulated on completing a randomised trial of de-escalated radiotherapy in patients with p16-positive oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma. The authors report progression-free survival, local regional control, freedom from distant metastases, and overall survival as secondary endpoints. The de-escalation protocol resulted in a reduction in progression-free survival, local regional control, and systemic control in patients who received de-escalated treatment with extracapsular extension compared with patients who received standard of care.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>[Correspondence] Misclassification of p16-positive, HPV-negative patients biases de-escalation trials – Authors&apos; reply</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1016/s1470-2045(25)00655-2</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1016/s1470-2045(25)00655-2</guid>
<pubDate>2025-12</pubDate>
<dc:creator>David M Routman; James S Lewis; Daniel J Ma</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>The Lancet Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1016/S1470-2045(25)00655-2</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: The Lancet Oncology | DOI: 10.1016/S1470-2045(25)00655-2</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>We appreciate the important points raised by Jessica T Lovett and colleagues regarding p16 immunohistochemistry as a surrogate for HPV status in oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma in de-escalation studies such as MC1675.1 As they noted, the prognostic implications of p16 and HPV discordance have been previously analysed, such as in a multinational study by Mehanna and colleagues.2 Patients who were p16-positive and HPV-negative had an increased rate of cancer recurrence (hazard ratio 1·92, 95% CI 1·42–2·60).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Unexpected Results of Induction Chemotherapy vs Adjuvant Chemotherapy</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoncol.2025.4092</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoncol.2025.4092</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Melvin L. K. Chua; Darren W. T. Lim</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoncol.2025.4092</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Oncology | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoncol.2025.4092</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>To the Editor We read with interest the results of the phase 3 randomized clinical trial by Guo et al that investigated the important question if induction chemotherapy (IC) was superior to adjuvant chemotherapy (AC) when added to a backbone of concurrent chemoradiotherapy (CCRT) in patients with N2-3 nasopharyngeal carcinoma (NPC). For IC, the investigators used the triplet combination of paclitaxel-cisplatin-fluorouracil (TPF), whereas doublet cisplatin-fluorouracil (PF) was used for AC. The trial was powered to detect a 12% difference in progression-free survival (PFS) in favor of IC, and enrolled 324 patients, with 162 patients in each group. However, this was a negative trial with comparable 3-year PFS between IC plus CCRT and CCRT plus AC, contrasting the results of the NPC-0501 trial by the Hong Kong NPC study group, which showed an improvement for PFS in favor of IC, albeit subtle differences exist between both trials. Intriguingly, in the present study, IC was associated with poorer local control compared with AC.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Definitive Radiotherapy for Organ Preservation in Nasal Cavity Cancers</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoncol.2025.5241</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoncol.2025.5241</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Nikhil P. Mankuzhy; Fan Yang; Lillian A. Boe; Chengcheng Gui; Yingzhi Wu; Nadeem Riaz; Yao Yu; Sean M. McBride; Achraf Shamseddine; Andy Shim; Dennis Mah; Lara A. Dunn; Loren S. Michel; David G. Pfister; Eric J. Sherman; Ian Ganly; Jennifer R. Cracchiolo; Snehal G. Patel; Richard J. Wong; Marc A. Cohen; Nancy Y. Lee</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoncol.2025.5241</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Oncology | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoncol.2025.5241</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>This cohort study evaluates the use of definitive rhinectomy and adjuvant radiotherapy with or without chemotherapy for patients who declined rhinectomy or had unresectable disease.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2024.3469</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2024.3469</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2024.3469</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2024.3469</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Mission Statement: To advance the patient-centered, evidence-based practice of otolaryngology–head and neck surgery by publishing scientifically rigorous and innovative research, reviews, and commentary. Our journal serves as a vital resource for clinicians, researchers, educators, and trainees by providing high-quality, peer-reviewed content focused on improving the understanding and treatment of ear, nose, and throat conditions. We are dedicated to fostering dialogue and action on critical issues in otolaryngology, including the education and training of health care professionals, quality improvement, and the ethics and economics of equitable health care delivery.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Mind, Machine, and Medicine</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4108</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4108</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>William (Bill) M. Lydiatt</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4108</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4108</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>This Viewpoint summarizes the presidential address of the president of the American Head and Neck Society.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Multiomic Selection of Cancer-Testis Antigens as Precision Immuno-oncologic Targets in Head and Neck Cancer</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.3563</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.3563</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Abdullah A. Memon; Musaddiq J. Awan; Oscar Villarreal Espinosa; Rachel Kuehn; Anne Frei; Jamie Foeckler; Jennifer Bruening; Kenneth Akakpo; Becky Massey; Michael Stadler; Stuart Wong; Heather A. Himburg; Joseph Zenga</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.3563</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.3563</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Importance Head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC) is an aggressive malignant neoplasm with an increasing need for precision therapeutics. Cancer-testis antigens (CTAs) represent promising targets given their aberrant tumor expression and otherwise localized expression to immune-privileged tissues with no (testis-restricted) or minimal (testis-selective) expression in other human body sites. Despite their potential, limited studies rigorously evaluate CTAs as therapeutic targets in HNSCC. Objective To orthogonally validate and present specific CTAs as potential precision immuno-oncologic targets in both previously untreated (de novo) and recurrent HNSCC tumors. Design, Setting, and Participants This was a cross-sectional study conducting multiomic analyses on a single academic tertiary care center’s tumor registry from 2018 to 2023, with validation using publicly available transcriptomic datasets. A total of 33 tumor samples from patients with HNSCC, including both de novo and radiation-recurrent tumors, were analyzed. Data were analyzed from August to December 2024. Main Outcomes and Measures The primary outcome was the identification and rigorous validation of specific CTAs with tumor-specific expression in HNSCC. Results This study analyzed 33 HNSCC institutional tumor specimens, including 25 de novo and 8 radiation-recurrent tumors. Of 33 included patients, 25 (76%) were male, 8 (24%) were female, and the median (range) age was 61 (29-87) years. Tumor subsites included the oral cavity (24 [73%]), larynx (7 [21%]), and oropharynx (2 [6%]). Tumors were primarily T4a (23 [70%]), with nodal involvement in 16 (48%). Initial analysis of bulk RNA-sequenced institutional data and single-cell RNA-sequenced external data identified several CTAs ( DKKL1 , SPANXB1 , SPANXD , and ACTL8 ) upregulated in recurrent tumors. An expanded reanalysis revealed that CTAs were expressed across HNSCCs, including robust expression not only in radiation-recurrent disease but also in de novo tumors. Immunohistochemistry was performed on ACTL8 to confirm transcriptional level findings at the protein level, which showed moderate focal cytoplasmic staining in tumor tissue. To refine the tumor-specific CTA list, an exclusionary analysis using single-cell RNA-sequenced data from normal oral mucosa was conducted, removing any CTAs with any expression in normal tissue. This resulted in a final list of 23 testis-restricted and 44 testis-selective CTAs specific to HNSCC, of which 14 CTAs overlapped across all transcriptomic datasets. Finally, using CopyKAT, CTAs were specifically enriched in malignant epithelial populations compared with benign populations within the same patients with HNSCC. Conclusions and Relevance In this study, a set of 23 testis-restricted and 44 testis-selective CTAs were orthogonally validated in multiple tumor datasets. Of these, a core set of 14 CTAs were consistently detected across all datasets. Their tumor specificity and broad expression bolster their potential as promising precision immuno-oncologic targets for future T-cell receptor engineering efforts.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Are We Training Too Many Head and Neck Fellows?</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.3471</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.3471</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>William (Bill) M. Lydiatt</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.3471</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.3471</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>This Viewpoint discusses the purpose of head and neck fellowship and what the correct number of practicing head and neck surgeons is.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Reimbursement for Thyroid Surgery and Potential Solutions</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.3696</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.3696</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Philip R. Brauer; David Octeau; Benjamin Wajsberg; Eric D. Lamarre; Jamie A. Ku; Mario Skugor; Danielle M. Bottalico; Natalie L. Silver; Brandon L. Prendes; Joseph Scharpf</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.3696</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.3696</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Importance In 2024, the US Senate Committee on Finance released a white paper outlining future reforms to the Medicare payment models. Objective To characterize trends in Medicare reimbursement for thyroid surgery and to provide evidence for future discussions on payment reforms. Design and Setting This retrospective economic evaluation used data on reimbursement for thyroid surgeries from the Centers for Medicare &amp;amp;amp; Medicaid Services’ Physician Fee Schedule from 2000 to 2023. Data were analyzed from May to June 2024. Main Outcomes and Measures The main outcomes were reimbursement rates for thyroid surgery and changes in reimbursement over time. Dollar amounts were adjusted to January 2023 US dollars. Annual reimbursement was averaged nationally, and compound annual growth rate and Pearson correlation coefficient were used to characterize trends. Results Between 2000 and 2023, Medicare reimbursement for thyroid surgeries decreased 38.7%, from $1517.59 to $929.55, when adjusted for inflation. The reimbursement for total thyroidectomy demonstrated the greatest decline at 47.8%, from $1803.16 to $942.07. Thyroid lobectomy and completion thyroidectomy both had reduced reimbursements at 41.7% (from $1250.38 to $729.02) and 25.5% (from $1499.26 to $1117.54), respectively. The compound annual growth rate for thyroid surgeries as a whole was 0.4% when not adjusted for inflation and −2.1% when adjusted for inflation. There was 0% growth in work relative value units between 2012 and 2023 for all thyroid surgeries. Conclusions and Relevance This economic evaluation found an almost 40% decrease in the rate of reimbursement for thyroid surgery, with total thyroidectomy having the greatest decrease at 47.8%. These findings provide evidence that current trends are not sustainable. Thyroid surgeons should take a proactive approach to improving reimbursements before these changes impact patient access to thyroid surgery.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Contralateral Tonsil in p16-Positive Tonsil Squamous Cell Carcinoma</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2410</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2410</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Louis-Xavier Barrette; Michelle Gentile; Karthik Rajasekaran</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2410</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2410</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>This Viewpoint examines current surgical guidelines and emerging evidence regarding the optimal treatment of patients with p16-positive oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Improving Palliative Care for Patients With Head and Neck Cancer</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2688</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2688</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Christine G. Gourin; Thomas J. Smith; Rebecca A. Gersten</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2688</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2688</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>In this issue of JAMA Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery, Fu et al used data from the Ontario Cancer Registry to evaluate palliative care (PC) use in 11 135 patients with head and neck cancer (HNC) during their last year of life. They found that PC was utilized in 90% of patients and was associated with increased monthly costs at the end of life, a greater number of emergency department visits and hospital admissions, and a lower likelihood of dying at home compared to non-PC recipients. The majority of PC was received in the inpatient setting and was initiated in the last 6 months of life. Gastrostomy and/or tracheostomy tube placement occurred in 11% of patients in the last year of life and was associated with increased costs that were partially mitigated by early (&gt;6 months before death) PC involvement. The authors conclude that early PC involvement may attenuate the costs associated with tracheostomy and gastrostomy tube use in the last year of life but that it does not reduce the use of aggressive hospital-based care or facilitate home deaths. These findings highlight the high symptom burden associated with HNC end-of-life care and demonstrate gaps in the current delivery of PC to this population.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Palliative Care With Tube Use and End-of-Life Quality and Costs in Head and Neck Cancer</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2687</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2687</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Rui Fu; Rinku Sutradhar; Qing Li; Noémie Villemure-Poliquin; Kelvin K. W. Chan; Irene Karam; Julie Hallet; Antoine Eskander</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2687</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2687</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Importance Patients with head and neck cancer (HNC) have high utilization rates of tracheostomy or gastrostomy tubes (g-tubes) at the end of life, with accompanying high costs. It is unknown whether the timing of palliative care (PC) initiation may attenuate the cost or be associated with better quality of life during the last year and more home deaths. Objective To assess the association of palliative care (first exposure) and tracheostomy or g-tube utilization with end-of-life costs among patients with head and neck cancer during the last year of life. Design, Setting, and Population This was a population-based cohort study of adults diagnosed with HNC between January 1, 2007, and December 31, 2022, who died before October 1, 2023, in Ontario, Canada. Health administrative data were deterministically linked and analyzed at the ICES (formerly Institute for Clinical Evaluative Sciences). Data analysis was conducted from January 2024 to June 2025. Exposures Timing of PC, categorized as early (12 to 6 months before death), late (&amp;amp;lt;6 months before death), and none (no PC during last year of life), was combined with tracheostomy tube use (binary) to form a 6-level categorical variable. This procedure was repeated for g-tube. Main Outcomes Mean monthly health care costs in last 6 months of life were estimated using a patient-level case-costing algorithm using 2023 CAD$ (CAD$ 1.00 = US$ 0.74) and evaluated by negative binomial regression. Results The analysis included 11 135 adults who received a diagnosis of HNC from 2007 to 2022 and died before October 1, 2023. They had a mean (SD) age of 68.4 (12.1) years at diagnosis and 8245 were male (74.0%). Nearly 90% received PC: 5866 (52.6%), late PC; 4093 (36.8%), early PC; and 1176 (10.6%) did not receive PC. Regarding tracheostomy/g-tube use in the last year of life, 1293 (11.6%) used a tracheostomy and 1235 (11.1%), a g-tube. Compared to those who did not receive PC nor use a tracheostomy tube, the cost increase on using a tracheostomy tube (rate ratio [RR] 2.93; 95% CI, 2.32-3.71) was higher than using it with early PC (RR, 2.88; 95% CI, 2.63-3.15) but lower than using it with late PC (RR 4.37; 95% CI, 4.00-4.77); results were similar for g-tube use. A large proportion of the cohort had an emergency department visit (9109 [81%]) or a non-PC hospital admission (5419 [48.7%]) in last 6 months of life, with both proportions being the lowest among nonrecipients of PC. Early PC was associated with a 46.8% lower likelihood (odd ratio, 0.53; 95% CI, 0.45-0.63) of experiencing a home death than no PC. Conclusions and Relevance This cohort study found that receiving a tracheostomy/g-tube in last year of life has pronounced economic implications to the health care system. Early initiation of PC may attenuate this high cost but may not reduce the use of aggressive hospital-based care at the end of life or facilitate home deaths. Team-based early provision of PC for this patient population is required.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Barriers and Timely Postoperative Radiation Therapy in Head and Neck Cancer</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2824</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2824</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Megan T. Nguyen; Emily Kistner-Griffin; Reid DeMass; Bhisham S. Chera; Chanita Hughes Halbert; Katherine R. Sterba; Elizabeth G. Hill; Brian Nussenbaum; Anthony J. Alberg; Vlad C. Sandulache; David J. Hernandez; Ryan S. Jackson; Sidharth V. Puram; Russel Kahmke; Nosayaba Osazuwa-Peters; Gail Jackson; Sue S. Yom; Evan M. Graboyes</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2824</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2824</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Importance Initiation of postoperative radiation therapy (PORT) within 6 weeks of surgery is associated with improved outcomes among patients with head and neck squamous cell carcinoma. However, the relationship of barriers to care with timely PORT is unknown. Objective To categorize barriers to timely PORT, evaluate the association of barriers to care with initiation of timely PORT, and describe the primary reason for delay among patients without timely PORT. Design, Setting, and Participants This prospective cohort study at a US academic medical center included adults with head and neck squamous cell carcinoma undergoing curative-intent surgery with an indication for PORT. Patients were recruited for the study from May 19, 2020, to November 6, 2023. Main Outcomes and Measures The primary outcome was initiation of timely PORT, defined as starting radiation therapy within 6 weeks of surgery. Barriers to PORT were prospectively collected via patient self-report and the electronic health record. Among patients who did not start PORT within 6 weeks of surgery, the primary reason for delay was defined as the singular barrier category that most directly led to the delay. Results Among 78 patients (mean [SD] age, 61.5 [10.8] years; 54 males [69.2%]), 32 patients (41%) initiated PORT within 6 weeks of surgery, and 46 patients (59%) did not initiate PORT within 6 weeks of surgery. Each additional barrier was associated with a decreased odds of initiating timely PORT (adjusted odds ratio, 0.81 [95% CI, 0.63-1.01]); patients with 5 or more barriers had a 76% reduction in the odds of starting PORT within 6 weeks of surgery relative to those with 0 to 2 barriers (adjusted odds ratio, 0.24 [95 CI%, 0.06-0.84]) on multivariable analysis. When analyzed by barrier category, patients with a perioperative adverse effects–related barrier were less likely to initiate timely PORT than patients without a perioperative adverse effects barrier (adjusted odds ratio, 0.17 [95% CI, 0.04-0.66]) on multivariable analysis. Among patients without timely PORT, the most common primary reason for delay was a barrier related to poor care coordination (19/46 [41.3%]). Conclusions and Relevance In this prospective cohort study, patients with a greater number of barriers and those with a barrier related to the perioperative adverse effects category were less likely to initiate timely PORT. Among patients without timely PORT, the most common primary reason for delay was a barrier related to poor care coordination. Efforts to improve timely PORT should focus on decreasing the number of barriers, improving surgical quality, and enhancing care coordination.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Preexisting Psychiatric Risk Factors and Any and Long-Term Opioid Use in Head and Neck Cancer</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2649</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2649</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Nosayaba Osazuwa-Peters; May Z. Gao; Russel R. Kahmke; Shreya P. Ramkumar; Nicole E. Bates; Jeffrey F. Scherrer</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2649</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2649</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Introduction Head and neck cancer (HNC), one of the most emotionally distressing cancers, carries a significant burden of psychiatric comorbidities. While opioids are commonly prescribed in cancer care, the association between preexisting psychiatric risk factors and prescription opioid use in HNC remains unclear. Objective To test the hypothesis that preexisting psychiatric risk factors are associated with any opioid prescription and long-term opioid therapy in patients with HNC. Design, Setting, and Participants This retrospective longitudinal cohort study used deidentified data from the Optum electronic health record database, comprising a random sample of 5 million patients across the US between January 2010 and December 2018. Eligible patients were adults diagnosed with HNC. Using a 2-year look-back prior to the index date of HNC diagnosis, patients who used prescription opioids prior to HNC diagnosis were excluded. The data analysis was conducted between July 2022 and July 2023. Main Outcomes and Measures Outcomes of interest were receipt of any prescription opioid within 12 months of index HNC and long-term opioid therapy (LTOT), defined as 10 or more opioid prescriptions within 12 months of index HNC. Psychiatric risk factors included anxiety disorders, depression, smoking/nicotine dependence, substance use disorders, and benzodiazepine prescription. Multivariate logistic regression estimated the odds of opioid use based on preexisting psychiatric factors. Results Of 20 286 patients with an HNC diagnosis, 11 335 met all eligibility criteria. Patients in the analytic cohort had a mean (SD) age of 57.1 (15.5) years, and 55.4% were female. Within 12 months of HNC diagnosis, 23.4% received an opioid prescription, and 4.9% received LTOT. In fully adjusted models, depression (adjusted odds ratio [aOR], 1.21; 95% CI, 1.01-1.45), nicotine dependence (aOR, 1.56; 95% CI, 1.40-1.73), and benzodiazepine comedication (aOR, 1.44; 95% CI, 1.22-1.70) were associated with increased odds of receiving any opioid prescription. Furthermore, male patients had 49% greater odds of receiving opioid prescriptions (aOR, 1.49; 95% CI, 1.36-1.64). Only smoking/nicotine dependence was associated with increased odds of LTOT (aOR, 1.77; 95% CI, 1.21-2.61). Conclusions and Relevance Preexisting psychiatric comorbidities, especially depression and smoking/nicotine dependence, were associated with increased odds of prescription opioid use and LTOT in patients with HNC in this longitudinal cohort study. Screening for these comorbidities during the management of patients with HNC can be impactful in informing clinical decisions that contribute to safer opioid prescribing.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Unilateral vs Bilateral Transoral Surgery for Tonsil SCCa</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2235</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2235</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Andrew M. Peterson; Lucas Cruz; Michael P. Wu; Spencer R. Bockover; Dorina Kallogjeri; Lauren H. Yaeger; Alex Harbison; Paul Zolkind; Jason T. Rich; Patrik Pipkorn; Randal C. Paniello; Sidharth V. Puram; Ryan S. Jackson</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2235</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2235</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Importance Transoral surgery via a radical tonsillectomy followed by pathology-guided adjuvant therapy is standard of care for tonsillar squamous cell carcinoma (SCCa). There is significant variation in the management of the contralateral tonsil without clinical evidence of disease. Objective To assess the second primary tumor rates, oncologic survival, functional outcomes, and complications between bilateral and unilateral transoral surgery for tonsillar SCCa. Data Sources A search of Embase, Ovid MEDLINE, Scopus, and Cochrane was performed on September 11, 2024. Study Selection Inclusion criteria were studies with more than 10 adults undergoing transoral surgery for unilateral tonsillar SCCa reporting at least 1 primary or secondary outcome. Screening of abstracts and full texts along with data extraction were performed in duplicate. Data Extraction and Synthesis The Meta-analysis of Observational Studies in Epidemiology ( MOOSE ) reporting guideline was followed. Data were pooled using a random-effects model. Main Outcomes and Measures The primary outcome measure was the synchronous and metachronous contralateral tonsil second primary tumor rates. Secondary outcome measures were between-group differences in oropharyngeal hemorrhage and gastrostomy tube dependence rates and 2-year and 5-year overall survival (OS) and disease-free survival (DFS). Results Of 136 unique citations identified, 11 studies were included, representing a total of 1486 patients (634 bilateral surgery, 852 unilateral surgery). The synchronous contralateral tonsil second primary tumor rate in the bilateral surgery group was 4.0% (95% CI, 2.0%-5.0%; I 2 = 0.05%). The metachronous contralateral tonsil second primary tumor rate in the unilateral surgery group was 0.1% (95% CI, 0%-1%; I 2 = 0.04%). There were no between-group differences in oropharyngeal bleeding rate (−0.2% [95% CI, −5.6% to 5.3%]) or gastrostomy tube dependence rate (−0.5% [95% CI, −5.2% to 4.3%]). The 2-year and 5-year pooled OS proportion differences between the bilateral surgery and unilateral surgery groups were 3.6% (95% CI, −2.2% to 9.4%) and 5.3% (95% CI, −3.8% to 14.4%), respectively. The 2-year and 5-year pooled DFS proportion differences between the bilateral surgery and unilateral surgery groups were −0.5% (95% CI, −6.5% to 5.4%) and 11.1% (95% CI, 1.6%-20.5%), respectively. Conclusions and Relevance This systematic review and meta-analysis suggests that omission of contralateral elective extracapsular tonsillectomy in tonsillar SCCa is safe with markedly low metachronous contralateral tonsillar second primary tumor rates and no compromise in survival. The decision to perform a simultaneous contralateral extracapsular tonsillectomy can be addressed via clinician-patient shared decision-making with consideration of its pros and cons.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Emerging Role of Pathologic Response in Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma Immunotherapy</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2111</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2111</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Ashish Dahal; Ravindra Uppaluri; Trisha M. Wise-Draper</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2111</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2111</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Immune checkpoint inhibitors (ICIs) have transformed the treatment of recurrent and metastatic head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC), but combination studies in the definitive disease setting with concurrent chemoradiation have been disappointing. New results from the KEYNOTE-689 phase 3 trial suggest the addition of neoadjuvant followed by adjuvant pembrolizumab in the perioperative setting may represent a new standard of care for resectable locally advanced HNSCC. Pembrolizumab improved event-free survival (EFS) by a median of 21.4 months compared to standard therapy. This trial also established safety in the surgical setting; similar proportions of patients in both the treatment and control arms successfully completed surgery. These findings may transform the treatment landscape of resectable locally advanced HNSCC, where current 3-year progression-free survival remains between 49% and 64%. While the contribution of components, neoadjuvant and/or adjuvant, in KEYNOTE-689 remains undefined, identifying which patients are most likely to benefit from ICI therapy in the definitive setting is an important goal.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Pathologic Treatment Effect and Survival in HPV-Negative HNSCC Following Neoadjuvant Nivolumab</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1707</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1707</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Annie E. Moroco; Kathryn Nunes; Angela Alnemri; Kelly Bridgham; Pablo Llerena; Madalina Tuluc; Stacey Gargano; Tingting Zhan; Arielle G. Thal; David M. Cognetti; Joseph M. Curry; Jennifer M. Johnson; Adam J. Luginbuhl</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1707</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1707</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Importance Neoadjuvant immunotherapy shows promise in the treatment of head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC). Pathologic treatment effect (pTE) is one way to assess response to treatment; however, the association of this response with survival outcomes is not yet clear. The current study sought to determine whether treatment response to neoadjuvant nivolumab, as measured by pTE, correlates with survival outcomes. Objective To determine whether patients with HNSCC with pathologic response to neoadjuvant nivolumab have improved survival outcomes. Design, Setting, and Participants A cohort study performing a pooled analysis of 2 multi-institutional neoadjuvant clinical trials ( NCT03238365 , NCT03854032 ) enrolling patients from July 2017 to January 2022, was performed. Patients with resectable HNSCC enrolled in 1 of 2 clinical trials and treated with neoadjuvant immunotherapy and surgical resection were included in the analysis. Patients were followed up for a median (range) of 36 (4-72) months. Analysis took place on April 15, 2024. Intervention Patients were treated with neoadjuvant nivolumab with or without the addition of immunomodulating medications (tadalafil or indoleamine 2,3 dioxygenase inhibitor). Main Outcome and Measure Pooled analysis was performed to plot Kaplan-Meier 3-year survival outcomes for pTE responders and low or nonresponders. A pTE response threshold was determined using recursive partitioning analysis. Results Seventy-nine patients were included in the analysis, of whom 40 (51%) had human papillomavirus (HPV)–negative disease. Recursive partitioning analysis identified a pTE threshold of 57%, which was used to define pathologic responders vs low or nonresponders. Pathologic responders with HPV-negative disease had significantly improved disease-free survival (100% for responders vs 66.8% for low or nonresponders; 95% CI, 46.1%-80.6%) and overall survival (100% for responders vs 73.3% for low or nonresponders; 95% CI, 53.4%-85.7%). In patients with HPV-positive disease, disease-free survival was high for both responders (90%; 95% CI, 47.3%-98.5%) and low or nonresponders (92.4%; 95% CI, 72.8%-98.1%). Conclusion and Relevance This cohort study found that patients with HPV-negative disease who are deemed pathologic responders (pTE &amp;amp;gt;57%) to neoadjuvant nivolumab may have improved survival outcomes compared with those who are low or nonresponders. Not only does this suggest a role for using pathologic response as a surrogate marker, but it further highlights the neoadjuvant strategy in HNSCC as associated with improved survival.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Patients With Head and Neck Cancer and High Health Care Costs</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1976</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1976</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Noémie Villemure-Poliquin; Rui Fu; Qing Li; Kennedy Ayoo; Kelvin K. W. Chan; Irene Karam; Frances C. Wright; Natalie G. Coburn; Julie Hallet; Antoine Eskander</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1976</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1976</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Importance The care for a small subset of patients is responsible for a disproportionately large share of health care expenditures. Head and neck cancer is associated with significant health care costs due to complex treatment regimens and long-term sequelae. Given this high baseline cost, identifying patients with high care costs within a population with cancer might help inform interventions to optimize resource allocation. Objective To characterize patients with head and neck cancer with the highest health care costs during the first year after diagnosis. Design, Setting, and Participants A population-based, retrospective cohort study was conducted using administrative data from the Institute for Clinical and Evaluative Sciences in Ontario, Canada, and included adults diagnosed with head and neck cancer between January 2007 and October 2020 (identified from the provincial cancer registry) with a full 1.5-year follow-up from the date of diagnosis to the date of death or October 31, 2021. The total 1-year health care costs were estimated using a patient-level algorithm and were collected in 2020 Canadian dollar values. The main analyses were performed in April 2023 and a sensitivity analysis was performed in April 2025. Main Outcomes and Measures High health care costs (&amp;amp;gt;75th percentile) during the first year after a head and neck cancer diagnosis. Predictors of high health care costs were identified using a multivariable logistic regression model. Results The cohort included 13 795 patients (mean age, 63.2 [SD, 11.7] years and 3452 [25.0%] were female), 3448 (25%) of whom had high health care costs. Cancer stage was the strongest predictor of high health care costs. Compared with patients with stage I cancer, those with stage II cancer had 2-fold greater odds for high health care costs (odds ratio [OR], 3.14 [95% CI, 2.56-3.84]), those with stage III cancer had 5-fold greater odds for high health care costs (OR, 6.08 [95% CI, 4.99-7.41]), and those with stage IV cancer had 8-fold greater odds for high health care costs (OR, 8.94 [95% CI, 7.43-10.80]). Receiving multiple treatment modalities also was associated with greater odds for high-cost care. Conclusions and Relevance This cohort study found that more advanced disease stage and receiving multiple treatment modalities were the strongest predictors of high-cost care among patients diagnosed with head and neck cancer. Prioritizing research and implementation of screening programs, earlier cancer diagnoses, and effective treatment deescalation strategies might mitigate a significant portion of these high costs.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Unilateral vs Bilateral Transoral Robotic Surgery for HPV-Positive Tonsillar Squamous Cell Carcinoma</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1833</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1833</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Andrew M. Peterson; Spencer R. Bockover; Dorina Kallogjeri; Katherine Chang; Theresa Tharakan; R. Alex Harbison; Paul Zolkind; Jason T. Rich; Patrik Pipkorn; Randal C. Paniello; Sidharth V. Puram; Ryan S. Jackson</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1833</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1833</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Importance The palatine tonsil is the most common subsite of human papillomavirus (HPV)–related oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma (SCC). There is debate on how to manage the contralateral clinically uninvolved tonsil in patients undergoing a primary surgical approach via transoral robotic surgery (TORS). Objective To assess postoperative complications, functional outcomes, contralateral tonsil second primary rates, and survival in patients undergoing unilateral vs bilateral TORS with pathology-guided adjuvant treatment. Design, Setting, and Participants A retrospective cohort study was carried out in a quaternary care academic medical center. All consecutive unilateral tonsillar patients with SCC undergoing TORS as primary treatment from June 2016 to July 2023 were included. Analysis was conducted between October 1, 2024, and January 1, 2025. Exposure Unilateral TORS (ipsilateral radical tonsillectomy) vs bilateral TORS (ipsilateral radical tonsillectomy and contralateral extracapsular tonsillectomy). Main Outcomes The primary outcome measure was rate of postoperative oropharyngeal hemorrhage. Secondary outcome measures included postoperative emergency department (ED) visit/hospitalization rate, time to nasogastric tube (NGT) removal, rate of discharge with an NGT tube, G-tube dependence rates, second primary rates in the contralateral tonsil, length of stay, and 2-year and 5-year disease-free survival (DFS) and overall survival (OS). Results A total of 158 (106 unilateral, 52 bilateral TORS) patients with HPV-associated tonsillar SCC were evaluated, including 18 women and 139 men with a mean (SD) age of 60 (10) years. There were clinically meaningful differences in oropharyngeal hemorrhage rates (7% vs 15%; percent difference, −7.8; 95% CI, −18.8% to 3.2%), 30-day ED visit/hospitalization rates (9% vs 21%; percent difference, −11.7%; 95% CI, −24.1 to 0.7), and median length of stay (2 vs 3 days) for unilateral and bilateral TORS, respectively. Swallowing outcomes, DFS, and OS were not significantly different between the 2 groups. A total of 3 patients (1.9%) had a second primary tumor in the contralateral tonsil, including 2 metachronous primary tumors in the unilateral group (1.8%) and 1 synchronous primary tumor incidentally removed at the time of surgery in the bilateral group (1.9%). Conclusions and Relevance This cohort study found that omission of contralateral elective extracapsular tonsillectomy in HPV-positive SCC was safe and associated with a trend toward lower posttonsillectomy hemorrhage, postoperative ED visits for pain control, and hospital length of stay without compromising survival. Prophylactically resecting the contralateral tonsil may add patient harm without any clear benefits.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Considerations and Cautions in Postoperative Circulating Tumor HPV DNA Kinetics</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1612</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1612</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Molly E. Heft Neal; Richard L. Bakst; Raymond L. Chai</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1612</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1612</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Human papillomavirus (HPV)–associated oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma (OPSCC) is a rapidly evolving field in which HPV circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) has emerged as a promising biomarker for cancer response and minimal residual disease (MRD) detection. In a study published in JAMA Otolaryngology-Head &amp; Neck Surgery, Yin et al investigate the kinetics of postoperative HPV ctDNA in a cohort of patients undergoing primary surgery for HPV-OPSCC. In this prospective study of 84 patients, 57 (82.6%) had detectable pretreatment samples. Of those, 35 patients had blood draws at both specified time points: postoperative day (POD) 1 to 2 and postoperative week (POW) 2. Similar to previous studies, these data support a correlation between preoperative HPV ctDNA levels and tumor stage, size of nodal disease, and presence of extranodal extension. The crux of this recent work, however, focuses on the positive and negative predictive values in addition to specific timing considerations of postoperative circulating tumor DNA detectability. Of 35 patients with complete blood draws, 16 (45.7%) remained detectable at POD 1 to 2; however of these, only 3 continued to be detectable at POW 2. These data yield a negative predictive value of 95% (95% CI, 74%-100%) and a positive predictive value of 19% (95% CI, 4%-46%), highlighting the superior reliability of the 2-week time point for MRD assessment. The authors propose an algorithm whereby patients with detectable samples on POD 1 to 2 undergo repeat testing at POW 2 if being used to guide adjuvant decisions. This 2-step approach balances timely risk stratification with avoidance of overtreatment, recognizing that adjuvant therapy planning requires a lead time of up to 6 weeks for multidisciplinary coordination. Of note, use of MRD for adjuvant decisions is currently restricted to clinical trials as this is not yet standard of care.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Postoperative ctHPVDNA Kinetics in Patients With HPV-Related Oropharyngeal Cancer</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1606</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1606</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Linda X. Yin; Cecelia M. Hidalgo; Aaron W. Bogan; Danielle E. Hunter; Kathleen R. Bartemes; Kendall K. Tasche; Eric J. Moore; Daniel L. Price; Daniel J. Ma; Michelle A. Neben-Wittich; Scott C. Lester; Katharine A. Price; Patrick W. McGarrah; Harry E. Fuentes Bayne; David M. Routman; Kathryn M. Van Abel</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1606</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1606</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Importance Circulating tumor human papillomavirus DNA (ctHPVDNA) is an important biomarker for the presence of HPV-associated oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma (OPSCC), but little is known about early postoperative kinetics of ctHPVDNA clearance. Objective To investigate early postoperative kinetics of ctHPVDNA in patients with HPV-associated OPSCC. Design, Setting, and Participants This prospective cohort study was conducted at a single tertiary care center from January 4, 2020, to January 26, 2023. Patients with newly diagnosed HPV-associated OPSCC undergoing surgical management were enrolled. HPV status was defined as positive if findings of p16 immunohistochemistry and/or HPV DNA in situ hybridization and/or E6/E7 RNA in situ hybridization were positive. Exclusion criteria included history of prior head and neck cancer and metastatic disease at presentation. Data were analyzed from September 1, 2024, to April 25, 2025. Exposures Transoral robotic surgery with concurrent neck dissection. Main Outcomes and Measures Blood was drawn prior to surgery (pretreatment), 1 to 2 days after surgery (postoperative days 1 to 2), and approximately 2 weeks after surgery (postoperative week 2; range, 8 to 20 days). ctHPVDNA was quantified by a tumor tissue–modified viral (TTMV) HPV DNA test. Correlations were tested between the pretreatment and postoperative day 1 to 2 TTMV HPV DNA levels using Gaussian regression. Concordance between detectability at postoperative day 1 to 2 and postoperative week 2 was explored using negative predictive value and positive predictive value. Results Of 57 included patients with detectable pretreatment TTMV HPV DNA, 51 (89%) were male, and the median (IQR) age was 59 (54-66) years. A total of 35 patients (61%) had blood draws at all 3 time points; 16 (28%) had detectable TTMV HPV DNA on postoperative day 1 to 2. Pretreatment and postoperative day 1 to 2 TTMV HPV DNA levels had a medium positive linear correlation ( r = 0.31; 95% CI, 0.04-0.54). Undetectable TTMV HPV DNA on postoperative day 1 to 2 blood draw had a negative predictive value of 0.95 (95% CI, 0.74-1.00) for an undetectable level on postoperative week 2 blood draw, but a detectable level on postoperative day 1 to 2 blood draw only had a positive predictive value of 0.19 (95% CI, 0.04-0.46). Of the 16 patients with detectable TTMV HPV DNA pretreatment and at postoperative day 1 to 2, only 3 (19%) continued to have detectable TTMV HPV DNA at postoperative week 2. One patient had undetectable levels at postoperative day 1 to 2 and detectable levels at postoperative week 2. Conclusions and Relevance In this study, ctHPVDNA detectability early after surgery did not predict detectability at 2 weeks after surgery. ctHPVDNA clearance early after surgery could predict a negative test at 2 weeks. A negative blood draw finding on postoperative day 1 may be used to omit a postoperative blood draw at 2 weeks for minimal residual disease detection in future clinical trials.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Efficacy of a Brief Cognitive Behavioral Treatment Across Body Image Distress Domains</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.0965</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.0965</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Haley Hullfish; Emily Kistner-Griffin; Stacey Maurer; Wendy Balliet; Jessica Vanderlan; Olga Slavin-Spenny; Lynne Padgett; Angie Rush; Brad Johnson; Taylor McLeod; Ella J. Starr; Kenneth J. Ruggiero; Katherine R. Sterba; Evan M. Graboyes</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.0965</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.0965</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>This secondary analysis of a randomized clinical trial evaluates whether a brief, tailored cognitive behavioral treatment program is effective across multiple domains of head and neck cancer–related body image distress.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Pathologic Response and Survival After Neoadjuvant Immunotherapy for HNSCC</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4573</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4573</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Eric V. Mastrolonardo; Emma De Ravin; Praneet C. Kaki; Leonard E. Estephan; Kathryn Nunes; Hannah Kenny; Kelly Bridgham; Jason Tasoulas; Scott H. Koeneman; Richard A. Goldman; Christopher Fundakowski; Arielle Thal; David M. Cognetti; Jennifer M. Johnson; Adam J. Luginbuhl; Joseph M. Curry</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4573</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4573</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Importance Numerous phase 2 trials have evaluated the efficacy of neoadjuvant immune checkpoint inhibition (ICI) for mucosal head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC), using some degree of pathologic treatment response as a primary or secondary end point. However, whether pathologic treatment response is a meaningful surrogate end point for survival has yet to be determined. Objective To systematically assess the association between pathologic treatment response and overall survival (OS) and disease-free survival (DFS) after neoadjuvant ICI. Data Sources A systematic search of the PubMed, OVID Medline, Embase, CINAHL, and Cochrane databases was performed from January 1, 2000, through May 31, 2025. Study Selection Peer-reviewed studies investigating neoadjuvant ICI for the treatment of mucosal HNSCC in patients 18 years and older were identified. Full-length English-language articles that presented pathologic treatment response and survival data (OS and/or DFS) and any association between the 2 were included. Data Extraction and Synthesis Three blinded reviewers independently extracted study characteristics, pathologic treatment response data, and survival data, including hazard ratios (HRs) and CIs when available, according to PRISMA guideline. Data were compiled for statistical analysis to calculate DFS, OS, and HRs using a random-effects model. The I 2 index was used to report data heterogeneity. Main Outcomes and Measures HRs for the association of pathologic treatment response with DFS and OS. Results Eleven trials involving 451 patients met inclusion criteria, with 368 patients included in this meta-analysis. Nine nonrandomized and 2 randomized studies were included, including 7 cohort studies, 2 randomized clinical trials, and 2 retrospective cohort studies, each with a different neoadjuvant ICI regimen. Pooled analysis demonstrated that overall (primary tumor plus lymph node) partial pathologic response (PPR; ≤50% residual viable tumor; HR, 0.53; 95% CI, 0.28-0.97; I 2 = 2.1%) and major pathologic response (MPR; ≤10% residual viable tumor; HR, 0.34; 95% CI, 0.12-0.93; I 2 = 0.0%) were both associated with improved DFS up to 2 years. PPR and MPR were not associated with improved OS. Nine of 11 studies were at low risk of bias. Conclusions and Relevance Study findings suggest that overall PPR and MPR are associated with improved DFS. These data provide additional support for the potential use of pathologic treatment response as a surrogate for DFS after neoadjuvant ICI in resectable mucosal HNSCC.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Thyroid Lobectomy and Neck Dissection for N1b Papillary Thyroid Carcinoma</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4653</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4653</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Daniel W. Scholfield; Lillian A. Boe; Alana Eagan; Helena Levyn; Fergal Kavanagh; R. Michael Tuttle; Ashok R. Shaha; Jennifer R. Cracchiolo; Jatin P. Shah; Richard J. Wong; Snehal G. Patel; Ian Ganly</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4653</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4653</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Importance Patients with papillary thyroid carcinoma (PTC) with lateral neck metastases (N1b) are usually treated with total thyroidectomy (TT), neck dissection, and adjuvant radioactive iodine (RAI). This philosophy comes with higher risks of complications and sequela than thyroid lobectomy (TL) and neck dissection alone. There are no prior studies on patients from the Western hemisphere that compare survival and recurrence outcomes between these groups. Objective To compare recurrence and survival outcomes in propensity-matched TL vs TT + RAI patients who presented with ipsilateral N1b PTC at a tertiary cancer center in the US. Design, Setting, and Participants This cohort propensity-matched study was conducted at a single US tertiary cancer center included 37 TL patients and 37 of 561 TT + RAI patients (after excluding patients with M1 disease), with a median (IQR) follow-up of 113 (58-241) and 90 (48-185) months, respectively. Adult patients with PTC with lateral neck node metastases (N1b) were identified from a thyroid cancer database. The study included patients undergoing surgery at Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center from 1986 to 2020, inclusive, and the study was conducted from 2024 to 2025. Main Outcomes and Measures Overall survival (OS), disease-specific survival (DSS), and recurrence-free survival (RFS). Results Of 598 total individuals, the median (IQR) age was 41 (33-55) years, and 341 (57%) were female. The 5-year OS was 96.9% in the TL group and 96.8% in the TT + RAI group (hazard ratio [HR], 0.2; 95% CI, 0.03-1.58). The 5-year DSS was 96.7% in the TL group and 100% in the TT +RAI group. The 5-year RFS was 89.8% in the TL group and 88.9% in the TT + RAI group (HR, 1.48; 95% CI, 0.39-5.58). The survival rates did not change between 5 and 10 years. Conclusions and Relevance This cohort study found that a select group of patients with N1b PTC treated with TL had no important difference in survival and recurrence outcomes compared with patients treated with TT + RAI. Therefore, TL is an effective and safe treatment option in carefully selected and appropriately counselled patients with N1b PTC with unilateral tumors and low-volume regional lymph node metastases without clinical extranodal extension.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Pembrolizumab in Head and Neck Cancer—Promise and Price</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4624</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4624</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Lauren E. Miller; James W. Rocco; Vinay K. Rathi</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4624</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4624</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>This Viewpoint considers the financial impact of expanding the indication of pembrolizumab for treatment of resectable locally advanced head and neck squamous cell carcinoma expressing programmed cell death 1 ligand 1.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Factors Associated With Opioid Refills After Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4576</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4576</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Lingyi Zhang; Tammy Ly; Kimberly Luu; Megan Durr; Steven Pletcher; Ilya Likhterov; Andrew Murr; Zhonghui Guan</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4576</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery | DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4576</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Importance Persistent opioid use after otolaryngology–head and neck surgery (OHNS) is concerning. However, evidence-based guidelines for managing opioid refill prescriptions within 90 days after discharge, a critical period for the transition from acute to persistent opioid use, are lacking. Objective To identify perioperative risk factors associated with opioid refills at 1 to 30, 31 to 60, and 61 to 90 days after OHNS procedures. Design, Setting, Participants This cohort study used opioid prescription data from a large academic medical center. The study included adult patients, regardless of opioid-naive status, who underwent inpatient OHNS procedures and were discharged between January 2017 and December 2023. Exposure OHNS with a postoperative hospital stay of at least 1 day. Main Outcomes and Measures The primary outcomes were opioid refills at 1 to 30, 31 to 60, and 61 to 90 days after discharge. Results Among 4132 adult patients, the median (IQR) age was 62 (49-72) years, and 1870 (45.3%) were female. From 2017 to 2023, despite a substantial reduction in the total oral morphine equivalents (OME) of discharge opioid prescriptions after OHNS procedures, opioid refill rates remained unchanged. In multiple logistic regression analysis, underprescription (adjusted odds ratio [AOR], 1.60 [95% CI, 1.24-2.06]) and overprescription (AOR, 1.58 [95% CI, 1.29-1.95]) of discharge opioid daily doses (defined as ≥7.5 OME lower or higher than the patient’s inpatient opioid consumption during the last 24 hours before discharge), compared with a matched prescription, were associated with increased odds of refills within 30 days of discharge. Overprescription was also associated with increased odds of refills at 31 to 60 days (AOR, 1.34 [95% CI, 1.03-1.75]). Other factors associated with increased odds of refills at various time points included preoperative use of opioids, benzodiazepines, and cannabis; higher postsurgical pain levels; receiving a prior refill; and receiving an opioid prescription despite not using any inpatient opioids during the last 24 hours of hospitalization. Conclusion and Relevance This cohort study identified independent perioperative risk factors for opioid refills after inpatient OHNS procedures and proposes an evidence-based strategy to reduce refill risk.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Development of a simplified scoring system for MRI-detected retropharyngeal lymph node features to optimize AJCC 9th edition N classification in nasopharyngeal carcinoma</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006542?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006542?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: February 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 173 Author(s): Qin Liu, Jing-Ni Wei, Jia-Yu Zhou, Chuan-Run Zhang, Liang-Ru Ke, Nian Lu, Ying Deng, Yu-Wen Kuang, Yu-Chen Hua, Meng-Wen Wang, Jie Gong, Shu-Hui Dong, Longjunyu Wu, Xing Lv, Yan-Qun Xiang, Xiang Guo, Wei-Xiong Xia</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Jaw-in-a-day (JIAD) for malignant indications: A systematic review</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006529?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006529?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: February 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 173 Author(s): Jessica Trac, Rashi Ramchandani, Pallavi Dutta, Leba Sarkis, Robert Calvisi, Noémie Villemure-Poliquin, Joel Davies, Eszter Somogyi-Ganss, Nick Blanas, Karl Cuddy, Danny Enepekides, Kevin Higgins, Justine Philteos, Antoine Eskander</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Trans-hairline robotic neck dissection and robotic microvascular free flap reconstruction in oral cavity cancer</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006487?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006487?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): Velda Ling-Yu CHOW, Valerie Wai-Yee HO, Arthur Shing-Ho LO</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Letter to the editor: Stroke risk after head and neck cancer diagnosis and treatment in a Real-World clinical cohort</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525005342?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525005342?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): Cunxi Zou</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Methodological considerations in profiling the immune microenvironment and HPV status of oral multiple primary cancers</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006517?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006517?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): Shanshan Yuan, Jingjing Gao</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Refining surveillance in surgically treated HPV(+)OPSCC: The path to Risk-Adapted strategies</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006414?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006414?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): Jiaqian Wu, Jianning Zhang, Jiachuan Lin, Yan Huo</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>The diagnostic trade-off in post-treatment surveillance for HPV-positive oropharyngeal carcinoma</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S136883752500627X?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S136883752500627X?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): Yaling Tang, Heng Gan, Xin Gan</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Intrathyroid thymic carcinoma diagnosed following an odontogenic infection: Insights from a rare clinical presentation</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006268?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006268?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): Hitoshi Miyashita, Haruka Saito, Masashi Katoh, Fumiyoshi Fujishima, Nobuo Ohta</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Influencing factors on occurrence and prognosis of oral squamous cell carcinoma after organ transplantation</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006530?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006530?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): Yiheng Feng, Maged Ali Al-Aroomi, Jie Chen, Saiwen Song, Canhua Jiang, Jie Wang</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Treatment and outcome for 2,111 patients with vermilion lip squamous cell carcinoma: A nationwide, population-based study from the SweHNCR</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006475?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006475?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): A. Hafström, E. Hammerlid, M. Beran, M. Olin, A. Högmo, L. Farnebo</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Is 55 years an optimal age cutoff point for clinical staging in T1 papillary thyroid cancer?</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006463?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006463?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): Daixing Hu, Zhuolin Dai, Yang Feng, Xinliang Su, Chun Huang</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>A pilot study of a digital workflow for navigated tumor bed marking to reduce clinical target volume during adjuvant radiotherapy for oral squamous cell carcinoma</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006499?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006499?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): Frederik Holdorf, Henning Schliephake, Kathi Goldstein, Lennart Johannes Gruber, Phillipp Brockmeyer, Martin Leu, Stefan Rieken, Boris Schminke</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Patient-derived 3D organoid platform for functional assessment of GPC3-targeted CAR T cell cytotoxic activity in head and neck squamous cell carcinoma</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006438?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006438?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): Han-Na Yoon, Jin-ha Kim, Doeon Gu, Jonghyun Lee, Soo Yoon Kim, Hye Jin Kim, Jaehyeon Jeong, Dongkwan Shin, Yuh-Seog Jung, Man Ki Chung, Sang-Jin Lee, Sung Yong Choi</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>&lt;em&gt;NOTCH1&lt;/em&gt; loss promotes chemo and radio-resistance in head and neck cancer</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S136883752500644X?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S136883752500644X?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): Mushfiq H. Shaikh, Walid Gazala, Cindy Zheng, Mahdi Farzad Naimi, Matthew Cecchini, Amir Karimi, Halema Khan, Krista Joris, Shengjie Ying, Harrison Pan, Mohd Wessam Al Jawhri, David A. Palma, Joe S. Mymryk, Peter YF. Zeng, John W. Barrett, Anthony C. Nichols</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Integrated geriatric assessment and intervention in the head and neck oncology care pathway reduces adverse events and does not affect survival</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006402?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006402?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): Beniamino Vincenzoni Padovan, Marleen Beenker, Johannes A. Langendijk, Hans Paul van der Laan, Boukje A.C. van Dijk, Geertrudia H. de Bock, Boudewijn E.C. Plaat, Pauline de Graeff, Suzanne Festen, Gyorgy B. Halmos</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Neoadjuvant tislelizumab plus chemotherapy in locally advanced oral and oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma: A single-arm phase II clinical trial</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006384?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006384?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): Wen-Jie Wu, Pu-Gen An, Zi-Qi Zhang, Li-Hang Shen, Jian-Yun Zhang, Yan Chen, Ming-Wei Huang, Shu-Ming Liu, Jie Yao, Jie Zhang</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Blinded comparative evaluation of GPT-generated, online search-derived, and guideline-based answers for HPV-associated oropharyngeal cancer</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006426?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006426?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): Sholem Hack, Rebecca Attal, Karin Geva, Armin Farzad, Shibli Alsleibi, Naseem Saleh, Ben Gvili, David Yogev, David Shahal, Benyamin Meir Kaminer, Eric Remer</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Incidence of HPV-independent second primary malignancies following treatment of HPV-associated malignancy</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006190?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006190?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): Sarah C. Nyirjesy, Yana Al-Inaya, Selena Zhang, Omar A. Karadaghy, Derrick T. Lin, Daniel G. Deschler, Allen L. Feng, Mark A. Varvares, Adam S. Fisch, Daniel L. Faden, Jeremy D. Richmon</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Establishment and characterization of a new immortalized human oral keratinocyte (HOK) cell line harboring various &lt;em&gt;TP53&lt;/em&gt; mutations</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006281?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006281?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): Mei Zhao, Zhiyi Liu, Mutsuki Kawabe, Abdullah A Osman, Mitchell J. Frederick, Jeffrey N Myers</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Hpv-driven rewiring of the tumor immune microenvironment through single-cell profiling informs prognosis and therapy in HNSCC</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006189?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006189?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): Ying Li, Qianzi Kou, Chongyang Zheng, Pengkhun Nov, Changqian Wang, Peizan Ni, Lilin Li, Yangfeng Zhang, Duanyu Wang, Arzoo Prasai, Wen Fu, Jiqiang Li, Kunpeng Du</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Patterns of metastasis and nodal disease in tongue and buccal carcinomas: Case-based reflections in Delhi NCR Region</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006451?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006451?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): Kripa Bajaj, Ramya Ramadoss, Sandhya Sundar, Suganya Panneer Selvam, Hema Shree K.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Cerebrovascular events after head and neck radiation therapy: A systematic review and Meta-Analysis</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006396?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006396?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): Kennedy Ayoo, Elliot Koo, Noémie Villemure-Poliquin, Rui Fu, Jonathan C Irish, Thomas Lindsay, Antoine Eskander</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Survival rates and oncologic outcomes of adeno squamous carcinoma of oral cavity: A systematic review</title>
<link>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006505?dgcid=rss_sd_all</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1368837525006505?dgcid=rss_sd_all</guid>
<prism:publicationName>ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology</prism:publicationName>
<description>Journal: ScienceDirect Publication: Oral Oncology | DOI: DOI not found</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Publication date: January 2026 Source: Oral Oncology, Volume 172 Author(s): Francesco Chiari, Andrea Luigi Camillo Carobbio, Marco Ferrari, Piero Nicolai, Claudio Donadio Caporale, Pierre Guarino</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Feasibility and Adherence to Home‐Based Intensive Treatment Programs for Chronic Radiation‐Associated Dysphagia in Head and Neck Cancer Survivors—The HIT‐CRAD Trial</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70136</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70136</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2025 00:55:06 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Hanne Massonet; Ann Goeleven; Sandra Nuyts; Alice Vergauwen; Margot Baudelet; Fréderic Duprez; Peter Tomassen; Leen Van den Steen; Gwen Van Nuffelen</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70136</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70136</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background The HIT‐CRAD trial (ISRCTN57028065) is the first to combine home‐based non‐invasive brain stimulation with high‐volume strength and skill training over 8 weeks in patients with chronic radiation‐associated dysphagia (CRAD) following primary (chemo)radiotherapy for head and neck cancer. Methods Fifty‐four patients were randomized into three groups. Group 1 performed 8 weeks of strength training. Groups 2 and 3 combined 4 weeks of strength training with 4 weeks of skill training. Group 3 received high‐definition transcranial direct current stimulation (HD‐tDCS) during training. Group 2 received sham HD‐tDCS. Results Overall adherence and exercise adherence remained above 75% across all groups. Home‐based HD‐tDCS proved safe and feasible, with mild to moderate side effects (tingling, itching, or burning). Median exercise performance levels for strength training exercises ranged from 94% to 100%. Conclusions This study confirms the feasibility of high‐volume strength and skill training with HD‐tDCS in patients with C‐RAD. Proactive adherence‐supporting factors facilitate high adherence in this population. Both real and sham HD‐tDCS proved safe, feasible, and well tolerated. Trial Registration: International Standard Randomized Controlled Trials Number (ISRCTN) registry ID ISRCTN57028065</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Brain Metastases From Differentiated Thyroid Cancer in the Era of Targeted Therapies: A Multi‐Center Retrospective Cohort</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70139</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70139</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 07:04:44 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Liyona Kampel; Shaun Edalati; Eyal Yosefof; Anton Warshavsky; Gilad Horowitz; Nidal Muhanna; Hagit Shoffel‐Havakuk; Eyal Robenshtok; Aron Popovtzer; Inbar Finkel</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70139</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70139</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Brain metastases (BM) of differentiated thyroid carcinoma (DTC) are associated with unfavorable prognosis. This study evaluated BM management strategies and patients' outcomes. Methods A retrospective review of patients diagnosed with DTC and BM at Tel Aviv Sourasky and Rabin Medical Centers between 1985 and 2024. Clinical features, histopathology, treatments, and survival data were collected. Results Twenty patients were identified: 11 (55%) had papillary thyroid carcinoma, 8 (40%) had follicular carcinoma and 1 had Hurtle cell carcinoma. BM treatments included neurosurgical resection ( n = 9), stereotactic radiosurgery ( n = 14), and whole‐brain radiotherapy ( n = 6). Median survival following BM diagnosis was 16.2 months. Patients who did not undergo surgical resection had significantly shorter survival than those whose BM were resected (13 vs. 80 months, p = 0.03). Survival was also worse among patients receiving systemic therapy at the time BM developed (8.9 vs. 80 months, p = 0.0001). Conclusion Unresected BM of DTC and those arising during systemic therapy portend high mortality.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Differences in Survival Following Surgery Versus Chemoradiotherapy for Clinical Stage T4a Laryngeal Squamous Cell Carcinoma: A Propensity Score‐Matched Analysis</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70114</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70114</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 23:15:30 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Beverly J. Fu; Alexandra L. Potter; Patrik Pipkorn; Kristen L. Kraimer; Michelle M. Chen; Karthik Rajasekaran; Chi‐Fu Jeffrey Yang; Jake J. Lee</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70114</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70114</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Although laryngeal cancer incidence has declined in the United States, case fatality has risen. The survival equivalence of surgery versus chemoradiotherapy (CRT) for cT4a laryngeal squamous cell carcinoma (LSCC) remains uncertain. Methods We conducted a retrospective cohort study of cT4a LSCC patients treated with curative‐intent surgery or CRT using the National Cancer Database (2010–2021). Those receiving neoadjuvant or palliative therapy, or with distant metastases were excluded. Survival was assessed using Kaplan–Meier and Cox models after 1:1 propensity score matching. Results Among 3569 patients (mean age 61.0, 708 female), 2437 (68.3%) underwent surgery while 1132 (31.7%) received CRT. In the matched cohort ( n = 452 per arm), median survival was 52.8 (95% CI: 45.6–62.4) versus 37.6 (95% CI: 29.2–45.4) months for surgery versus CRT. Adjusted HR for CRT relative to surgery was 1.26 (95% CI: 1.02–1.57). Conclusions Surgery was associated with improved overall survival compared with definitive CRT in patients with T4a LSCC.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Neutrophil to Lymphocyte and Lymphocyte to Monocyte Ratios Predict Improved Survival and Response to Induction Chemotherapy in Locally Advanced Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Larynx</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70132</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70132</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 23:00:44 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Zachary Risch; Emily Bellile; Moneb S. Bughrara; Paul L. Swiecicki; Keith Casper; Kelly Malloy; Norman Hogikyan; Matthew Spector; Andrew Shuman; Chaz Stucken; Steven Chinn; Douglas C. Chepeha; Shruti Jolly; Michelle Mierzwa; Carol Bradford; Avraham Eisbruch; Thomas Carey; Mark Prince; Gregory T. Wolf; Francis P. Worden</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70132</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70132</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background University of Michigan Cancer Center (UMCC) protocol 9520 treated stage III/IV locally advanced squamous cell carcinoma of the larynx (LASCCL) with cisplatin and 5‐fluorouracil to select for definitive therapy based on response. Studies have shown that neutrophil‐lymphocyte ratio (NLR) and lymphocyte‐monocyte ratio (LMR) are potential prognostic markers in p16‐negative LASCCL. This study analyzes the predictive value of NLR and LMR. Methods Samples from 193 LASCCL patients treated with chemotherapy were reviewed. Response to induction chemotherapy was tested with logistic regression. Optimal cut‐points were determined by Youden's index. Survival was tested with Cox proportional hazards models. Results LMR had a positive association, NLR had a negative association with response to chemotherapy ( p = 0.004;0.07). Response was higher in patients with LMR ≥ 2.8 ( p = 0.0007) and NLR ≤ 2.8 ( p = 0.04). Overall and disease‐specific survival improved with LMR ≥ 2.8 ( p = 0.0002;0.004) and NLR ≤ 2.8 ( p = 0.10;0.03). Conclusions Low NLR and high LMR were associated with favorable responses to chemotherapy and survival in LASCCL.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Traumatic Intrathyroidal Hematoma: Case Report and Review of Literature</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.28248</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.28248</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Morgan Terry; Ana Araujo; Skylar Trott; Mark K. Wax</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.28248</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.28248</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Traumatic expanding intrathyroidal hematoma is rare and can be clinically obscured, leading to delayed diagnosis and potential airway compromise. Identification and prompt intervention are paramount to survival. Methods Patient presented to the emergency department as a modified trauma without signs of respiratory distress or enlarging neck circumference. Comprehensive trauma imaging identified the thyroid pathology prompting otolaryngology involvement. Results Rapid operating room arrangement allowed for prevention of airway compromise, straight forward intubation, and resolution of thyroid pathology prior to clinical decompensation. Conclusions We present an unusual case of traumatic thyroid hematoma in which the bleeding source was contained within the thyroid capsule; intubation and surgical intervention resolved the airway and thyroid pathology. Trauma‐indicated imaging allowed for identification in a clinically obscured pathology.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Magnifying Glass on Sinonasal NUT Carcinoma Heterogeneity via Spatial Transcriptomics</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.28231</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.28231</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Diana Bell; Garret Choby; Michelle Afkhami; Ellie Maghami; Renata Ferrarotto; Carl Snyderman; Eric Wang; Ehab Hanna; Raja Seethala</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.28231</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.28231</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Nuclear protein in testis (NUT) carcinomas (NCs) are rare, clinically aggressive tumors with characteristic translocation involving NUTM1 and BRD4 genes. While NCs are generally characterized by undifferentiated basaloid cells with focal/abrupt squamous differentiation, tumoral heterogeneity remains unexplored. This may have therapeutic implications as NC frequently develops drug resistance and metastasis. Spatial transcriptomics (ST) sequencing technology emerged as an approach to elucidate tumoral heterogeneity by integrating cellular transcriptome and spatial distributions within tissues, providing insights into the interactions among different cell types and overall tissue genomic architecture. Methods Three cases of sinonasal NC with formalin‐fixed paraffin embedded tissue formed the study material. A representative region of each NC was subjected to 10X Genomics Visium Spatial Gene Expression analysis. Resulting data were analyzed in 10X Genomics Loupe Browser. Results All cases demonstrated statistically distinct (graph‐neural network based) transcriptomic clusters. These clusters were correlated with histologic characteristics by parsing all spots by region types based on tissue distribution including tumor, limited stroma, and normal epithelium. Cluster constitution and transcriptomic pattern were consistent with the morphologic features of each tissue region. NC#3 had a relatively low number of tumor clusters in comparison to NC#1 and NC#2. Conclusions Spatial transcriptomic profiling corresponds to histopathologic features in NC and yet highlights cell type diversity across tumors and in the case of NC#2, within a given tumor. Behavioral correlates are speculative, but NC#3 for which the patient had a rapidly lethal outcome showed a preponderance of neural gene expression which may be of interest in tumor cell progression/evolution.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Epithelioid Hemangioendothelioma of the Head and Neck: A Systematic Review and an Institutional Case Study</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70087</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70087</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Gianluca Scalia; Valentina Zagardo; Gianluca Ferini; Eliana Giurato; Agata Bosco; Cinzia Molino; Mauro Pavone; Gianluca Galvano; Giovanni Federico Nicoletti; Giuseppe Emmanuele Umana; Francesca Graziano</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70087</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70087</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Epithelioid hemangioendothelioma (EHE) is a rare vascular tumor with variable clinical behavior, typically arising in the liver, lungs, and bones. Its occurrence in the head and neck region, including intracranial locations, is exceptionally rare and poses diagnostic and therapeutic challenges due to anatomical complexity and functional relevance. Objective To systematically review clinical features, diagnostic pathways, therapeutic strategies, and oncologic outcomes in patients with EHE involving the head, neck, and intracranial compartments. Methods A PRISMA‐compliant systematic review was performed across PubMed, Embase, Scopus, and Web of Science up to March 2025. Eighty‐three studies were included, encompassing 149 patients. Clinical, radiologic, histopathological, treatment, and outcome data were extracted and synthesized qualitatively. Results EHE showed a predilection for the oral cavity (41%) and cervical lymph nodes (30%), with intracranial involvement in 17%. The median age was 32 years; males predominated (1.9:1 ratio). Surgery was the mainstay treatment (87%), but recurrence (44%) and metastasis (38%) were frequent. Radiotherapy (13%) and chemotherapy (6%) were used selectively. Histologically, CD34 and CD31 positivity were predominant. Despite surgical resection with negative margins, disease progression was observed in 26% of cases, with 30% tumor‐related mortality. Conclusion Head and neck EHE is a clinically heterogeneous entity with high recurrence and metastatic potential. Complete surgical resection remains the cornerstone, but recurrence rates suggest a role for adjuvant therapy. Multidisciplinary management and long‐term follow‐up are essential. Further prospective studies and molecular profiling are needed to refine prognostic stratification and therapeutic strategies.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Malignant Transformation of Oral Leukoplakia and Proliferative Verrucous Leukoplakia and Its Biomarker Predictors: A Systematic Umbrella Review</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70073</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70073</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Mohammed Taib Fatih; Mohammed Khalid Mahmood; Balkees Taha Garib; Yad Mariwan Mohammed Amin; Ranjdar Mahmood Talabani; Tara Ali Rasheed; Handren Ameer Kurda; Balen Hamid Qadir; Zana Fuad Noori; Mohammed Aso Abdulghafor; Ariwan Othman Saeed; Herve Tassery; Delphine Tardivo; Romain Lan</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70073</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70073</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Oral leukoplakia (OL) represents the most common oral potentially malignant disorder globally, with highly variable reported malignant transformation (MT) rates creating challenges for evidence‐based clinical management. Objective To systematically synthesize evidence on MT prevalence in OL and evaluate potential predictive biomarkers through an umbrella review of systematic reviews and meta‐analyses. Methods Following PRISMA guidelines, we searched PubMed, MEDLINE, Scopus, and Embase databases through July 2025. Twenty‐seven systematic reviews encompassing more than 125,000 patients were included. Meta‐analyses were conducted using random‐effects models, with quality assessed using AMSTAR 2 and GRADE approaches. Results Transformation rates were considerably higher in proliferative verrucous leukoplakia (48%) than in OL (6%). Females exhibited almost twice the MT rate of males (64% vs. 35%), while tongue lesions showed the highest site‐specific risk (39%). The most promising predictive biomarker with a moderate level of evidence quality was DNA aneuploidy. Conclusions Because of its high malignant potential, OL necessitates risk‐based surveillance protocols. While the bulk of other predictors requires further investigation, DNA aneuploidy shows potential for clinical application.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Non‐Pharmacological Interventions for Improving Xerostomia Among Patients With Head and Neck Cancer: A Systematic Review and Network Meta‐Analysis</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70100</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70100</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Xueyan Cheng; Lizhen Wang; Mu‐Hsing Ho; Shing Fung Lee; Frederick K. Ho; Wing‐Fai Yeung; Chia‐Chin Lin; Denise Shuk Ting Cheung</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70100</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70100</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Xerostomia is highly prevalent among patients with head and neck cancer (HNC). This review aimed to compare the effectiveness of non‐pharmacological interventions (NPIs) for xerostomia among patients with HNC. Methods We systematically searched nine databases (inception–October 2024) for RCTs assessing the effects of NPIs on xerostomia (self‐reported xerostomia, incidence, stimulated/unstimulated salivary flow). Results Forty‐six trials (3802 patients) identified 10 arms: multimodal NPIs, herbal medicine, acupuncture, exercise, oral care, devices, health education, supplements, and active/passive controls. At post‐intervention, multimodal NPIs (the majority being herbal medicine combined with other therapies) ranked first for self‐reported xerostomia, incidence, and unstimulated flow versus other interventions. Herbal medicine ranked second for self‐reported and incidence of xerostomia and first for stimulated flow. Though lower‐ranked, acupuncture significantly improved all outcomes versus passive controls. Sensitivity analyses showed enhanced acupuncture efficacy with high‐dose radiotherapy. Conclusion Multimodal NPIs, herbal medicine, and acupuncture are promising for improving xerostomia among patients with HNC.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>On Behalf of Surgical Versus Non‐Surgical Treatment of Advanced Oropharyngeal Squamous Cell Carcinoma: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70083</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70083</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Alvaro Sanabria</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70083</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70083</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Head &amp;Neck, Volume 48, Issue 1, Page 317-318, January 2026.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Prognostic Significance of Solid Subtype of Papillary Thyroid Carcinoma: Analysis of 63 Patients</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.28266</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.28266</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Andre Ywata de Carvalho; Felipe D&apos; Almeida Costa; Jose Guilherme Vartanian; Luiz Paulo Kowalski</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.28266</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.28266</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Objective Solid subtype of papillary thyroid carcinoma (SSPTC) is an uncommon subtype of papillary thyroid cancer (PTC) and its prognostic significance is still controversial. The aim of this review is to present the clinicopathological features of SSPTC and compare its clinical behavior with classical PTC (cPTC). Methods We retrospectively analyzed patients who underwent thyroidectomy for SSPTC and compared the clinicopathological findings and clinical outcomes with those of patients with cPTC. Results Among 4937 patients treated for PTC, 63 (1.3%) were diagnosed with SSPTC, of which 76.2% were female, with a median age of 40 years, 3.2% had prior cervical irradiation, and the median diameter of the tumor was 15 mm. Compared to cPTCs, SSPTCs were larger (median tumor diameter: 15 vs. 9 mm), more symptomatic (non‐incidentally discovered) and were associated with an elevated risk for multifocality, extrathyroidal extension, lympho‐vascular invasion, lymph node metastasis, extra‐nodal extension, and distant metastasis. After a mean follow‐up of 58.5 months, rates of biochemical incomplete response to treatment and structural recurrence were higher when compared to those of cPTC. None of the patients who demonstrated an excellent response to treatment presented cancer recurrence during follow‐up. Distant metastasis occurred in 3 patients (4.8%). There were no cancer‐related deaths. Conclusions SSPTC is an aggressive histological subtype of PTC associated with adverse prognostic features, including larger tumor size, multifocality, and extrathyroidal extension, which correlate with a higher risk of cancer recurrence and therefore should be considered for accurate risk stratification, comprehensive management, and close follow‐up.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>A New Orthotopic Mouse Model of Laryngeal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70001</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70001</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Junrong Wang; Ming Song; Lei Wang; Xueying Wang; Xianguang Yang; Lunhua Guo; Jianfeng Chen; Hongxue Meng; Xionghui Mao; Erliang Guo; Susheng Miao</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70001</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70001</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background The aim of this study is to establish a novel and reproducible orthotopic mouse model, aiming to facilitate research related to laryngeal cancer. Methods Implantation of mouse squamous cell carcinoma cell line, Meer‐LUC, into the larynx of C57BL/6 mice ( n = 16). Tumor growth and survival were observed using magnetic resonance imaging and optical in vivo three‐dimensional imaging. Laryngeal and cervical lymph node specimens were obtained for HE staining and evaluation. Single‐cell sequencing was performed on laryngeal cancer patients, orthotopic mouse models, and subcutaneous tumor models to investigate the immune microenvironment of laryngeal cancer. Results We successfully established 15 cases of in situ laryngeal cancer mouse models. Tumors maintained steady growth at each observation time point, and histopathological evaluation confirmed the successful construction of the model. Single‐cell sequencing results suggest that the orthotopic model better simulates the immune microenvironment alterations of real laryngeal cancer. Conclusions We have developed a novel and reproducible orthotopic mouse model, which more faithfully mimics the immune system response of the human body and better simulates the biological evolution process of tumors. This model provides an essential animal research framework for investigating the molecular mechanisms underlying the occurrence and development of laryngeal cancer.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Does Modified 5‐Item Frailty Index Correlate With Survival in Oropharyngeal Squamous Cell Carcinoma?</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70005</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70005</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Marta Chmielecka; Rhona Hurley; Mohd Afid Mohd Slim; Nichola Philp; Matthew Donachie; Jan Horackiewicz; Josh McGovern; Katrina Knight; Nicholas J. W. Rattray; Claire Paterson; Catriona M. Douglas</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70005</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70005</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Introduction Oropharyngeal squamous cell cancer (OPSCC) is a common subtype of head and neck cancer. It is generally stratified into high, intermediate, and low risk prognostic groups on the basis of HPV (human papillomavirus) status and smoking history (Ang risk stratification). Frailty has been shown to have a negative survival effect in head and neck cancer. The effect of frailty on survival in OPSCC is unknown. The aim of this study was to explore overall survival (OS) and disease‐specific survival (DSS) in OPSCC based on the modified 5‐item frailty index (mFI‐5). Methods This was a retrospective cohort study of patients diagnosed with OPSCC in the West of Scotland. The mFI‐5 is a validated score that categorizes patients according to their level of frailty. Univariate and multivariate survival analyses were performed. Results One thousand and one patients with OPSCC diagnosed between 2012 and 2020 were identified. The median OS was shortened in both the 'Moderately Frail' (39 months) and 'Severely Frail' groups (11 months) compared with the 'Not Frail' group (82 months) ( p &lt; 0.001). DSS was shorter in the'Severely Frail' group (16 months) compared with the'Moderately Frail' group (66 months) ( p &lt; 0.001). However, after adjustment for other characteristics including HPV and PS (World Health Organization/Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group Performance Status), frailty was not significant on multivariate analysis. Conclusion Survival in patients with OPSCC decreases significantly with increasing frailty as measured by the mFI‐5. However, PS and HPV status are better predictors of OS and DSS.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Use of Deep Epigastric Composite Vascular Autograft in the Vessel Depleted Neck</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70010</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70010</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Jian‐Xun Chen; Andreea Gavrilescu; Shane D. Morrison; Pin‐Keng Shih</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70010</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70010</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Reconstructing the vessel‐depleted neck (VDN) is challenging due to prior surgeries and radiation compromising recipient vessels. The deep epigastric composite vascular autograft (DECVA) offers a novel solution by providing both arterial and venous conduits within a single pedicle. Methods From 2021 to 2023, seven patients with prior head and neck reconstructions underwent free flap reconstruction with DECVA. Preoperative imaging identified contralateral recipient vessels, and DECVA was harvested from the deep inferior epigastric artery and vein. Results All cases achieved successful anastomoses, with an average ischemia time of 157.3 min. No postoperative complications such as thrombosis, infection, or seroma were observed. Conclusion DECVA facilitates single‐stage free flap reconstruction in VDN, extending pedicle length while maintaining vascular integrity. This approach offers a viable alternative for complex cases with limited recipient vessels, expanding reconstructive options in microsurgery.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Feasibility and Efficacy of Indocyanine Green Angiography in Transoral Robotic Thyroidectomy: A Pilot Study</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70011</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70011</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Kyung Tae; Van Cuong Nguyen; Hae Won Choi; Dong Won Lee; Kyu Nam Kim; Gregory W. Randolph</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70011</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70011</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background This study aimed to evaluate the feasibility and effectiveness of indocyanine green (ICG) angiography in transoral robotic thyroidectomy (TORT). Methods A total of 130 patients with papillary thyroid carcinoma who underwent TORT with ICG angiography (ICG group, 65 patients) and without ICG angiography (control group, 65 patients) were analyzed. Results The parathyroid detection rate did not differ between the control and ICG groups. Among patients with total thyroidectomy, the incidence of postoperative transient hypoparathyroidism did not differ between the control (7/20, 35%) and ICG (4/20, 20%) groups. Pearson's correlation coefficients between the total ICG perfusion score and postoperative changes in serum intact parathyroid hormone and calcium levels showed statistical significance. Conclusions ICG angiography is feasible in TORT. Although it did not improve the parathyroid detection rate or reduce the incidence of hypoparathyroidism, ICG angiography was able to predict postoperative parathyroid function, as assessed by the total ICG perfusion score.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Oncological Impact of Surgical Margin Status After Transoral Laser Microsurgery for Early Glottic Cancer</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70013</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70013</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Sae Hatomi; Shuta Tomisato; Ken Kasahara; Hiroyuki Ozawa; Takeyuki Kono</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70013</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70013</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Transoral laser microsurgery is a well‐established treatment for early glottic cancer. However, managing patients with close/positive margins remains debated. This study analyzes the relationship between resection margins and oncologic outcomes. Methods Patients with early glottic cancer who underwent transoral laser microsurgery were included. We compared clinical characteristics, recurrence‐free survival, laryngeal preservation, and disease‐specific survival between negative and close/positive margin groups. Results Among 107 patients, 49 (45.8%) had close/positive margins. The recurrence‐free survival rate was significantly lower in the close/positive margin group. Anterior commissure involvement was a significant risk factor for recurrence. The median recurrence time for the close/positive margin group was 18.5 months, similar to the negative margin group. Laryngeal preservation and disease‐specific survival were similar between groups with &gt; 95%. Conclusions Patients with close/positive margins in early glottic cancer showed similar disease‐specific survival and laryngeal preservation rates as negative margins; despite lower recurrence‐free survival, suggesting a follow‐up approach is sufficient.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Fuel for Recovery: Predicting G‐Tube Dependence in HPV‐Negative Operable HNSCC</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70015</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70015</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Marie‐Michelle McNicoll; Alex M. Mlynarek; Keith Richardson; Michael Hier; Nader Sadeghi; Anna Casola; Nathaniel Bouganim; Khashayar Esfahani; Christina Tsien; George Shenouda; Khalil Sultanem; Marco A. Mascarella</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70015</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70015</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background HPV‐negative head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC) patients can face prolonged gastrostomy tube (g‐tube) dependence, affecting quality of life and delaying treatment. Existing models lack key health metrics like sarcopenia; this study develops a risk model to enhance preoperative assessment. Methods This study analyzed 265 HNSCC patients. Sarcopenia was assessed via cervical paraspinal skeletal muscle mass (C3) on CT scans. Patients requiring g‐tube support &gt; 28 days were identified. Risk models were developed and compared to the PEG Score. A 50‐patient validation cohort assessed model performance. Results Key predictors included male sex, sarcopenia, prior radiotherapy, and adjuvant therapy. Logistic regression (LR) model had the highest AUC (0.78); followed by Recursive Partitioning analysis (RPA) model (0.76), both outperforming the PEG Score (0.67). RPA model maintained superior accuracy in validation (AUC = 0.79). Conclusion RPA model outperformed PEG Score, offering a more precise risk tool for preoperative planning and early intervention.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Geographic Trends and Geospatial Analysis of Head and Neck Fellowship‐Trained Surgeons</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70016</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70016</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Jad Zeitouni; Harry May; Hannah Seo; Preston Thipaphay; Nosayaba Osazuwa‐Peters; Mark A. Varvares; Yusuf Dundar</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70016</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70016</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Disparities in access to otolaryngology and cancer care exist across the United States. However, little is known about the geographic distribution of fellowship‐trained head and neck cancer (HNC) surgeons. Methods A cross‐sectional study of American Head and Neck Society (AHNS) fellowship graduates from July 1, 1997 to June 30, 2022 was conducted. Geospatial and statistical analysis was conducted to assess current practice location and correlations with training regions. Results Among 688 graduates, 622 practice in the US or Canada. Most graduates remained in the region of their training. Geospatial analysis showed concentration of graduates in urban areas, with 152 of 3142 US counties having higher‐than‐expected density. Underserved regions were identified in the southeastern US, southern border, and western states. Conclusions Head and neck surgical fellowship graduates predominantly practice in large urban areas, leaving rural and underserved regions with limited access to complex HNC care. Strategic interventions are needed to address these gaps.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Survival Impact and Risk Factors of Cervical Lymph Node Metastasis in Maxillary Gingival Squamous Cell Carcinoma: A Retrospective Study of 81 Patients</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70021</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70021</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Takeshi Kuroshima; Naoya Kinoshita; Naoto Nishii; Yu Oikawa; Takuma Kugimoto; Hideaki Hirai; Hirofumi Tomioka; Yasuyuki Michi; Hiroyuki Harada</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70021</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70021</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background This study aimed to investigate the survival impact and predictive factors of cervical lymph node metastasis (CLNM) in patients with maxillary gingival squamous cell carcinoma (MGSCC). Methods This retrospective study included 81 patients with MGSCC who underwent radical surgery from 2008 to 2018. Results Pathological CLNM was observed in 24 patients, prevalently in levels IB and II on the ipsilateral side. Cox proportional hazards model analysis revealed histologic grade, CLNM, and local recurrence as independent prognostic factors for 5‐year disease‐specific survival. Multivariate analysis identified tumoral spread to the gingivobuccal sulcus and the maxillary tuberosity as independent risk factors for CLNM. Conclusions CLNM is associated with poor survival in patients with MGSCC. Primary tumors extending into the gingivobuccal sulcus or maxillary tuberosity may predict CLNM, particularly at levels IB and II. These findings may provide valuable insights for optimizing neck management strategies.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Evaluation of a Novel Prognostic System for Surgically Resected Oral Cavity Carcinoma</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70022</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70022</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Alisa Rybkin; Victor Lee; Melissa R. Young; Antoine Eskander; Barbara Burtness; Henry S. M. Park; Zain A. Husain</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70022</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70022</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background The Oral Cavity Predictive Score (OCCPS) is a point‐based system including T/N stage, LVSI, and grade that has been validated for predicting distant metastasis. We tested its ability to predict overall survival (OS) in surgically managed oral cavity carcinoma (OCC). Methods Patients diagnosed 2010–2020 and treated with surgery were selected from the National Cancer Data Base (NCDB) and stratified into standard, intermediate, and high‐risk categories using OCCPS. The Kaplan–Meier method compared OS in the whole cohort and select subgroups. Results Of 32 317 patients (median follow‐up 38.4 months), 51.7%, 22.5%, and 25.8% were classified into standard, intermediate, and high‐risk groups, respectively. Five‐year OS was 73.4%, 58.6%, and 39.3% (log rank p &lt; 0.001). The OCCPS stratified patients with negative margins and absent ENE, and stage IVA‐B disease (log rank p &lt; 0.001). Conclusion In patients with OCC managed with at least definitive surgery, the OCCPS successfully stratifies patients into standard, intermediate, and high‐risk groups for prediction of OS.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Tongue Surface Electromyography Detects Reduced Motor Unit Recruitment in Oropharyngeal Cancer Survivors With Hypoglossal Neuropathy</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70025</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70025</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Nathan J. Hansen; Katherine A. Hutcheson; Holly McMillan; Shitong Mao; Katelyn Vidad; Carly E. Barbon; Karin Woodman; Nicolaas C. Anderson; Benjamin Sanchez</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70025</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70025</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background This proof‐of‐concept case–control study examined the feasibility of tongue high‐density surface electromyography (HDS–EMG) to detect hypoglossal neuropathy. Methods We analyzed tongue HDS–EMG for N = 2 participants. Subjects were graded through clinical tongue functional measures and gold‐standard needle EMG. We collected HDS–EMG in three tongue tasks: relaxation, protrusion, and isometric maximum effort. The HDS–EMG was decomposed into motor unit spike train estimates. Results Muscle relaxation HDS–EMG contained spikes consistent with fasciculation potential morphology. During tongue protrusion, a case of confirmed CN XII neuropathy exhibited an elevated motor unit (MU) discharge rate and fewer MUs (45.71 peaks/s, 3 estimated MUs) compared to the control (11.63 peaks/s, 11 estimated MUs). During isometric contraction, the case exhibited an average discharge rate of 3.96 peaks/s on 3 MU estimates, whereas the control had a discharge rate of 2.58 peaks/s on 5 MU estimates. Conclusions Non‐invasive tongue HDS–EMG appears to show potential sensitivity for detecting reduced MU recruitment in hypoglossal neuropathy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Management of Retropharyngeal Lymph Node Metastases in Thyroid Cancer</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70027</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70027</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Isabelle Fournier; Ashwini Venkata Bandi; Sarah Hamidi; Priyanka Iyer; Naifa L. Busaidy; Maria E. Cabanillas; Ramona Dadu; Mimi I. Hu; Steven G. Waguespack; Ugur Nur Basmaci; Michelle D. Williams; Mena Mansour; Maria Gule Monroe; Neil D. Gross; Ryan P. Goepfert; Nancy D. Perrier; Victoria Banuchi; Jennifer R. Wang; Anastasios Maniakas; Mark E. Zafereo</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70027</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70027</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Retropharyngeal lymph node (RPLN) metastases in thyroid cancer are rare, with optimal management underreported. Methods Retrospective study of consecutive thyroid cancer patients with RPLN metastases treated at MD Anderson Cancer Center between 2000 and 2024. Results One hundred and sixty‐seven patients (75% differentiated, 21% medullary, 4% poorly differentiated thyroid cancer) were divided into three groups: active surveillance (AS) (13%), surgery (56%), and nonsurgical treatment (31%). In the AS group (median follow‐up 2.3 years), RPLN metastases grew a median 3% (range: 0–56) or 0.02 cm (range: 0–0.7) per year. Surgical therapy included transcervical (73%), transoral robotic (14%), transoral (12%), and transmandibular (1%) approaches. Median RPLN metastasis size was 1.7 cm (interquartile range: 1.3–2.2) at surgery. Three months post‐operatively, 11% had dysphagia and 1% had velopharyngeal insufficiency. Nonsurgical treatments included radioactive iodine (10%), radiation therapy (11%), and systemic targeted therapy (79%). Conclusion RPLN metastases grow slowly, and those ≥ 1 cm typically undergo surgical resection without significant long‐term morbidity.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Prognostic Impact of Age and Treatment Strategies in Elderly Patients With Oral Squamous Cell Carcinoma: An 11‐Year Retrospective Analysis</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70028</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70028</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Yuki Oikawa; Shoken Suzuki; Hidemitsu Igarashi; Yasunori Konno; Masato Yamazaki; Hiroshi Takano; Masayuki Fukuda</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70028</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70028</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Oral squamous cell carcinoma (OSCC) is becoming increasingly common in elderly populations, particularly in aging societies such as Japan. Methods This study retrospectively evaluated 312 OSCC patients treated at Akita University Hospital between 2011 and 2021, focusing on prognostic differences between elderly (≥ 75 years) and non‐elderly (&lt; 75 years) patients. Results Among the elderly patients, curative intent was associated with significantly better disease‐specific survival (DSS) and overall survival (OS) in comparison to palliative intent. The DSS for the elderly group was 83.2%; notably, it was 90.5% in patients who received curative intent and 42.9% in patients who did not receive curative intent. Conclusions This study emphasizes the importance of personalized treatment for elderly patients, suggesting that, even in advanced stages, curative intent can yield favorable outcomes in patients with acceptable general health. However, for those with severe comorbidities, palliative intent should be considered, focusing on quality of life.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Lip Reconstruction Following Cancer Resection</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70020</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70020</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Abbas M. Hassan; Michael M. Talanker; Peirong Yu; David M. Adelman; Mark T. Villa; Matthew M. Hanasono</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70020</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70020</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background An analysis of all possible lip defects and a comparison of outcomes following various reconstructive techniques is lacking in the literature. Methods An analysis of lip reconstructions following cancer resection from 1994 to 2024 was performed. Results A total of 221 patients underwent lip reconstruction. Tobacco use ( p = 0.003), diabetes mellitus ( p = 0.042), and concurrent mandible or maxillary reconstruction ( p = 0.019) were associated with surgical complications. Recurrent disease ( p = 0.011) and oral commissure resection ( p = 0.020) were associated with oral incompetence. Tobacco use ( p = 0.001) and defects involving both upper and lower lips ( p = 0.001) were associated with microstomia. Defects &gt; 50% of the lip had higher rates of oral incompetence ( p = 0.001) and microstomia ( p = 0.035). Conclusions Lip reconstruction outcomes are affected by patient‐related factors, defect characteristics, and reconstructive techniques. Oral commissure resection, extensive lip defects, and lip defects in combination with mandibulectomy and maxillectomy are most prone to adverse outcomes, and we use our results to propose a comprehensive treatment algorithm.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Association of PD‐L1 Expression With Tertiary Lymphoid Structures and Prognosis in Oral Cancer</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.28262</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.28262</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Emi Saitou; Mai Seki; Takaaki Sano; Masaru Ogawa; Satoshi Yokoo; Tetsunari Oyama</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.28262</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.28262</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Tertiary lymphoid structures (TLSs) are observed within invasive regions of malignancies. This study aimed to elucidate the relationship between programmed death‐ligand 1 (PD‐L1) expression and TLSs in oral squamous cell carcinoma (OSCC) and to assess their prognostic significance. Methods A total of 280 OSCC cases were analyzed. PD‐L1 expression was assessed via immunohistochemistry using biopsy and surgical specimens. Staining for immune cells was performed in cases exhibiting TLSs. Results Patients with high PD‐L1 expression and the presence of TLSs demonstrated significantly improved overall survival ( p &lt; 0.05). In contrast, in cases with low PD‐L1 expression, the presence of TLSs was associated with significantly poorer overall survival ( p &lt; 0.05). Conclusion OSCC cases with TLSs, high PD‐L1 expression is associated with a favorable prognosis, whereas low PD‐L1 expression correlates with significantly worse outcomes. This suggests that TLSs may be functionally heterogeneous, with distinct prognostic implications depending on PD‐L1 expression.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Late Toxicity and Long‐Term Quality of Life in Survivors of Cancer of the Major Salivary Glands More Than 5 Years After Diagnosis: A Multi‐National Study</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.28263</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.28263</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Susanne Singer; Cecilie Delphin Amdal; Kristin Bjordal; Bente Brokstad Herlofson; Guro Lindviksmoen Astrup; Andreas Boehm; Ulrike Wöhner; Eva Hammerlid; Ricardo Ribeiro Gama; Alexandre Arthur Jacinto; Femke Jansen; Irma M. Verdonck‐de Leeuw; Tatiana Dragan; Fréderic Duprez; Naomi Kiyota; Monica Pinto; Maximilian Krüger; Orlando Guntinas‐Lichius; Johanna Inhestern; Francesco Tramacere; Pierluigi Bonomo; Giuseppe Fanetti; Sandra Nuyts; Michaela Plath; Noa Stempler; Kristine Løken Westgaard; Katherine J. Taylor</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.28263</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.28263</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Because salivary gland cancers (SGC) are rare and include different tumor subtypes, data on their long‐term quality of life and late toxicities are sparse. Methods Multi‐national study including SGC survivors more than 5 years after diagnosis. They completed the European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) quality of life core questionnaire together with its head and neck cancer module and reported problems that were most bothering for them. Toxicity was clinically assessed. Results Altogether, 60 survivors from nine countries participated and reported dry mouth (mean score 37.2), use of painkillers (35.0), problems with sexuality (30.1), insomnia (28.9), fatigue (27.8), trismus (24.9), and sticky saliva (23.3). The most frequently mentioned long‐term problem was dry mouth , mentioned by a third of all participants. The most frequent toxicities were hearing impairment , soft tissue fibrosis , dry mouth , and cranial neuropathies . Conclusions Dry mouth is a frequent and disturbing problem in SGC survivors.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Thyroid Volume Measurement With AI‐Assisted Freehand 3D Ultrasound Compared to 2D Ultrasound—A Clinical Trial</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.28267</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.28267</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Klara Bay Rask; Fatemeh Makouei; Marcus Hans Jakowlew Wessman; Tina Toft Kristensen; Tobias Todsen</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.28267</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.28267</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Accurate thyroid volume assessment is critical in thyroid disease diagnostics, yet conventional high‐resolution 2D ultrasound has limitations. Freehand 3D ultrasound with AI‐assisted segmentation presents a potential advancement, but its clinical accuracy requires validation. Method This prospective clinical trial included 14 patients scheduled for total thyroidectomy. Preoperative thyroid volume was measured using both 2D ultrasound (ellipsoid method) and freehand 3D ultrasound with AI segmentation. Postoperative thyroid volume, determined via the water displacement method, served as the reference standard. Results The median postoperative thyroid volume was 14.8 mL (IQR 8.8–20.2). The median volume difference was 1.7 mL (IQR 1.2–3.3) for 3D ultrasound and 3.6 mL (IQR 2.3–6.6) for 2D ultrasound ( p = 0.02). The inter‐operator reliability coefficient for 3D ultrasound was 0.986 ( p &lt; 0.001). Conclusion These findings suggest that freehand 3D ultrasound with AI‐assisted segmentation provides superior accuracy and reproducibility compared to 2D ultrasound and may enhance clinical thyroid volume assessment. Trial Registration: ClinicalTrials.gov identifier: NCT05510609.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>A Novel Peculiarity of TXNIP Reversing the Radioresistance of NPC and Inducing Ferroptosis by xCT‐GSH‐GPX4‐ROS Axis</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70004</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70004</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Jin Zhou; Qi Zhou; Yan Mo; Hanghao Zhang; Ruiyue Dang; Min Lin; Runsha Xiao; Yiting Chen; Xin Deng; Shuanglian Wang; Chengmin Li; Jidong Hong; Chushuang Lin; Haoyang Tang; Jiahui Jiang; Zuozhong Xie; Xueping Feng</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70004</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70004</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Radioresistance is a major problem in clinical treatment of nasopharyngeal carcinoma (NPC), and molecular mechanisms of radioresistance related to the antioxidant system are unknown. TXNIP (thioredoxin‐interacting protein) is an endogenous inhibitor of thioredoxin. The system xCT/GSH/GPX4 axis is an important antioxidant system of ferroptosis in drug‐resistant solid tumor therapy. It is of great clinical significance to study TXNIP and ferroptosis in the role of NPC radioresistance for the therapeutic effect of NPC patients. Methods Immunohistochemistry, qRT‐PCR, and WB were used to analyze the expression of TXNIP in clinical samples and NPC cells. Clone formation detected the radioresistance of cells. Flow cytometry, immunofluorescence, and WB were used to analyze intracellular ROS levels and the expression of GPX4 and xCT. Related kits were used to analyze Fe 2+ , MDA, GSH, and mitochondrial membrane potential. A nude mice subcutaneous tumor formation experiment was used for further verification. Results TXNIP was less expressed in the NPC radioresistant group than in the radiosensitive group. Overexpression of TXNIP promoted apoptosis of NPC cells and showed a dose‐dependent response to radiation. In addition, with radiation, TXNIP increased intracellular ROS levels, decreased the expression of GPX4 and xCT, affected the production of intracellular metabolites, such as Fe 2+ , MDA, and GSH, and induced ferroptosis in cells. Stabilized overexpression/knockdown cells significantly affected the growth of tumors in nude mice with radiation. Conclusions TXNIP is a radiosensitive and ferroptosis‐associated gene, which can reverse the radioresistance of NPC by promoting ferroptosis in a dose‐dependent manner and through the xCT‐GSH‐GPX4‐ROS axis.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Aberrant Splicing Burden Predicts Immune Infiltration and Prognosis in Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinomas</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70007</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70007</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Sandhya Kalavacherla; Joseph Bendik; Mitchell Victor; Hannah Carter; Joseph A. Califano; Theresa Guo</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70007</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70007</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background The role of alternative splicing events (ASEs) in immune evasion and prognosis in head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSC) is not well characterized. Methods Using The Cancer Genome Atlas data, we identified ASEs (using our novel algorithm OutSplice) and characterized associations between splice burden, immune infiltration (quantified by xCell) and prognosis with multivariable logistic regression and survival models. Results HSNC tumors with low splice burden and high immune infiltration had significantly better prognosis than tumors with high splice burden and low immune infiltration when controlling for age, pathologic stage, HPV status, and tumor mutational burden (hazard ratio = 0.61). High splice burden predicted decreased immune infiltration in HNSC, which was validated in five other cancer types and supported by murine models of oral squamous cell carcinoma. Conclusions High splicing burden, as defined by OutSplice, is a novel biomarker to predict poor both immune infiltration and prognosis in HNSC.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Nasopharyngeal Endoscopic Resection Extended to the Internal Carotid Artery (Type 4): Technical Notes, Indications, and Outcomes</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70008</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70008</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Francesco Boaria; Alessandro Vinciguerra; Stefano Taboni; Martina Conti; Paola Costantino; Vittorio Rampinelli; Marco Valentini; Francesca Gennarini; Benjamin Verillaud; Elisabetta Zanoletti; Davide Mattavelli; Alberto Schreiber; Mario Turri‐Zanoni; Alberto Daniele Arosio; Piergiorgio Gaudioso; Paolo Battaglia; Maurizio Bignami; Paolo Castelnuovo; Philippe Herman; Piero Nicolai; Marco Ferrari</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70008</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70008</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Endoscopic surgical approaches for nasopharyngeal malignancies, including recurrent nasopharyngeal carcinoma (rNPC) and nasopharyngeal salivary gland tumors (NSGT), have seen significant development over the last decades. Our groups have expanded the classification of nasopharyngeal endoscopic resections (NER) from type 1 to 3 to incorporate internal carotid artery (ICA)‐including ablations. The aim of this work is to describe the surgical technique, indications, and preliminary oncological outcomes of NER extended to ICA, proposing it as type 4 NER. Methodology Consecutive patients affected by nasopharyngeal malignancies and treated with NER type 4 were included. Data on patient‐, disease‐, and treatment‐related factors were collected. Adverse events were classified from G1 to G5 according to the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events. Preliminary survival outcomes were measured. A detailed description of the surgical steps of NER type 4 was reported. Results A total of 13 patients were included: 7 NPC and 6 non‐NPC, of which 4 were primary adenoid cystic carcinoma (ACC), 1 was recurrent ACC, and 1 was polymorphous adenocarcinoma. After a median follow‐up of 34.7 months, 5 patients had a local recurrence during follow‐up after a median of 17.3 months, one of which died at 10.3 months after surgery. The cumulative ≥ G3 adverse event rate was 61.5%. No major complications directly associated with ICA occlusion were reported. Conclusions NER type 4 is a potential treatment alternative to (re)irradiation in highly selected patients with nasopharyngeal malignancies involving/abutting the ICA. The results reported should be considered preliminary; a novel description of the technique is provided.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Safety and Efficacy Findings From a Phase Ib/II Study of ASP‐1929 Photoimmunotherapy With Pembrolizumab in Recurrent and/or Metastatic Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70014</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70014</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>David M. Cognetti; Joseph M. Curry; Jennifer Johnson; Michael Kwon; Shirley Y. Su; Francisco Civantos; Coral Olazagasti; Joseph Valentino; Susanne M. Arnold; R. Bryan Bell; Michael K. Gibson; Kyle Mannion; Kathryn M. Van Abel; Katharine A. Price; Haiying Dong; Amy H. Thorne; Toshiaki Suzuki; Ann M. Gillenwater</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70014</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70014</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background ASP‐1929 photoimmunotherapy—cetuximab conjugated to IRDye 700DX and red light (690 nm) for localized drug activation—results in rapid, selective cell killing. Methods This phase Ib/II open‐label study evaluated ASP‐1929 photoimmunotherapy plus pembrolizumab in patients with recurrent/metastatic HNSCC (≥ 1 accessible lesion, PD‐L1 combined positive score ≥ 1, ineligible for standard locoregional therapy). Primary objectives were safety/tolerability and objective response rate (ORR). Secondary objectives included overall survival (OS) and progression‐free survival (PFS). Results Eighteen patients (median age 63 years, 74% male) comprised the photoimmunotherapy‐evaluable population. The confirmed ORR was 27.8% (95% CI 9.7–53.5); four of five responders had complete responses (95% CI, 6.4–47.6). Median OS was 25.6 months (95% CI, 14.6–not evaluable); median PFS was 2.9 months (95% CI, 1.4–14.6). The most common serious adverse reactions were dysphagia and tongue edema (each n = 2; 10.5%). Conclusions ASP‐1929 photoimmunotherapy plus pembrolizumab was generally tolerable, with promising efficacy in patients with recurrent/metastatic HNSCC.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Postoperative Radiotherapy for Head and Neck Merkel Cell Carcinoma: Sometimes, Less Is More</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70023</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70023</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Yuan Zheng; Di Zhang; Qihao Sun; Jiaoyang Lu</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70023</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70023</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Head and neck Merkel cell carcinoma (HNMCC) is a rare but aggressive malignancy characterized by high recurrence rates and an uncertain survival benefit from postoperative radiotherapy (PORT). This study aimed to develop and validate a prognostic nomogram for risk stratification and to evaluate the survival benefit of PORT across risk groups. Methods Patients with surgically resected, non‐metastatic HNMCC were retrospectively identified. Independent prognostic factors for overall survival (OS) were identified via univariate and multivariate Cox regression. A nomogram was constructed and internally validated using time‐dependent receiver operating characteristic curves, calibration plots, and decision curve analysis (DCA). Patients were stratified into high‐ and low‐risk groups based on nomogram scores, and the impact of PORT was assessed within each risk category using Kaplan–Meier analysis and log‐rank tests. Results A total of 1776 patients were included. Six variables—age, sex, marital status, race, T stage, and N stage—were independently associated with OS and used to construct the nomogram. The model demonstrated superior discriminative ability and calibration performance compared to traditional staging systems, and DCA confirmed improved clinical utility. Among high‐risk patients, PORT significantly improved 5‐ and 10‐year OS ( p &lt; 0.001), whereas no significant survival benefit was observed in the low‐risk group ( p &gt; 0.05). Conclusions This study presents a validated nomogram that accurately predicts survival and supports risk‐adapted use of PORT in HNMCC. Selective application of PORT based on individualized risk may optimize outcomes while minimizing overtreatment.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Application of a Saliva‐Based Liquid Biopsy for the Detection of HPV in Patients With Oral Cavity Squamous Cell Carcinoma (OCSCC)</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70003</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70003</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:34:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Michela Bulfoni; Alessandro Tel; Beatrice Krpan; Barbara Marcon; Maria De Martino; Giorgia Vesca; Cinzia Lombardo; Stefania Marzinotto; Emanuele Nencioni; Salvatore Sembronio; Corrado Pipan; Massimo Robiony; Francesco Curcio</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70003</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70003</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Human papilloma virus (HPV) is a DNA virus capable of infecting mucous membranes. In most cases, the infection is cleared by the immune system, but a prolonged exposure to HPV can progress to cancer. 40%–60% of head and neck squamous cell carcinomas (HNSCC) are linked to HPV, which is considered a risk factor especially among young people in industrialized countries. HNSCC are not identified early due to their slow growth and their locations not being easy to see. Despite the prognostic value of HPV, the use of HPV‐DNA as a diagnostic marker is not fully developed. HPV‐DNA can be detected in saliva specimens of patients with HPV‐driven cancers. Considering this, we employed saliva samples to optimize a non‐invasive RT‐PCR assay for HPV infection and prove the hypothesis that the presence of HPV DNA represents a risk factor for Oral Cavity Squamous Cell Carcinoma (OCSCC). The potential of this work is to highlight how an HPV screening program based on salivary testing can be useful for early cancer detection and patient monitoring. Methods In this retrospective study, 127 patients and 93 control samples were tested for the presence of HPV in self‐collected saliva specimens. Viral DNA was extracted from saliva using an automated instrument. A multiplex RT‐PCR was employed for the detection of the (28 most frequent HPV Types). Patients' demographics were collected in a clinical database. Statistics were performed by STATA16, and significance was set at p &lt; 0.05. Results Most patients had a diagnosis of OCSCC (49.1%), 38%–9% of which involved the tongue. 9.6% resulted positive for HPV DNA in saliva, specifically for high‐risk subtypes (42.9% type 58; 28.6% types 45, 59, 39 and 9.6% type 16, 18). HPV+patients were compared to those who were found negative. HPV infection was related to the TNM stage, especially with pT2N1 ( p ≤ 0.002) and with primary vs. relapsed tumors ( p = 0.004). Independent of site, the assay reached a sensitivity of 91.7%, a specificity of 100%, and an agreement of 98.5%, compared to the oropharyngeal swab ( Cohen's Kappa = 0.947; n = 65). Test PPV was 100% (95% CI 71.5–100), while NPV was 98.1% (95% CI 90.1–100). Conclusions Our findings indicate that salivary HPV testing is a non‐invasive and convenient test that could become part of routine clinical management for HPV infection of the oral cavity. This test represents an ideal mode of screening of asymptomatic individuals and a long‐term monitoring tool for HPV‐driven cancer patients.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Prognostic Value of Worst Pattern of Invasion‐5 on Low‐Risk and Early‐Stage Oral Tongue Cancer</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70135</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70135</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:24:54 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Ming‐Hsien Tsai; Hui‐Shan Huang; Chih‐Chi Chou; Hui‐Ching Chuang; Yu‐Tsai Lin; Hui Lu; Chih‐Yen Chien; Fu‐Min Fang</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70135</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70135</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background To evaluate the prognostic value of the worst pattern of invasion‐5 (WPOI‐5) for patients with pathologically early‐stage and low‐risk oral tongue squamous cell carcinoma (OTSCC). Methods A total of 224 patients treated between 2005 and 2016 were analyzed. WPOI‐5 was defined as tumor satellites ≥ 1 mm from the main tumor or nearest satellite. Its prognostic impact on cancer‐specific survival (CSS) and locoregional recurrence‐free survival (LRRFS) was assessed, and a WPOI‐5‐based nomogram was developed. Results Patients with WPOI‐5 had significantly worse 5‐year CSS and LRRFS (both p &lt; 0.001). In Cox analysis, WPOI‐5 independently predicted poorer CSS (HR 6.908, p = 0.006) and LRRFS (HR 14.910, p &lt; 0.001). Adding WPOI‐5 improved the nomogram's 5‐year LRRFS AUC from 0.789 to 0.842. Conclusions WPOI‐5 is an adverse prognostic factor in pathologically early‐stage, low‐risk OTSCC and may justify trials of adjuvant therapy in these patients.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Nomogram for Predicting Osteoradionecrosis After Fibula Free Flap for Mandibular Reconstruction</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70138</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70138</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 01:21:09 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Andrea Costantino; Bianca Festa; Filippo Marchi; Chung‐Kan Tsao; Raul Pellini; Luca Gazzini; Peter T. Dzięgielewski; Mario Ciniglio; Francesco Mazzola; Luca Calabrese; Antonio Sarno; Giampiero Parrinello; Linda Chow; Jyh‐Kwei Chen; Giorgio Peretti; Armando De Virgilio</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70138</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70138</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Osteoradionecrosis (ORN) is a severe complication following radiotherapy (RT), particularly after mandibular reconstruction with a fibula free flap. Risk prediction remains challenging due to limited data. Methods We conducted a multicenter retrospective study including 294 patients who underwent fibula free flap reconstruction and adjuvant RT. A predictive nomogram for ORN was developed using logistic regression with stepwise backward selection, validated via 10‐fold cross‐validation. Results ORN occurred in 9.9% of patients. Eight variables were retained in the final model, which demonstrated excellent discrimination (AUC = 0.94) and good calibration (mean absolute error = 0.017). The optimal threshold for classification was 0.30, with the model achieving a sensitivity of 1.0, specificity of 0.80, and an overall accuracy of 0.82. Conclusion This is the first nomogram developed to predict ORN following fibula free flap mandibular reconstruction. It provides a personalized risk estimate, supporting individualized clinical decision‐making and improved pre‐ and postoperative planning. Prospective validation is warranted.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Rates of ICU Delirium After Microvascular Free Tissue Transfer Reconstruction of the Oral Cavity and Oropharynx</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70137</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70137</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 23:37:46 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>William Nesmith; Shayan Fakurnejad; Danielle Gillard; Katherine Wai; Mary Jue Xu; Ilya Likhterov; Jonathan George; William Ryan; Ivan El‐Sayed; Patrick Ha; Andrea Park; Rahul Seth; P. Daniel Knott; Chase Heaton</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70137</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70137</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Microvascular free tissue transfer (MFTT) is the standard in the reconstruction of major head and neck defects, but involves extended hospital stays and an increased risk of post‐operative delirium (POD). What risk factors increase the risk of POD in patients undergoing MFTT, and subsequent complications? Methods Retrospective cohort study of 168 patients undergoing MFTT following ablation of oral cavity or oropharyngeal cancer. Patient demographic data, operative data, post‐operative ventilatory support needs, post‐operative complications, and post‐operative sedation and analgesic needs were collected, and the association with POD was evaluated. Results POD was significantly associated with opioid ( p = 0.0018) and sedation requirements ( p &lt; 0.001), postoperative return to the OR ( p = 0.002) and medical complications ( p = 0.033). There was no association with the rate of MFTT failure ( p &gt; 0.05). Conclusion In MFTT patients, opioid and sedative administration are potentially modifiable factors that may be able to reduce POD incidence and optimize the postoperative course of patients undergoing MFTT.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Application of Acellular Dermal Matrix With or Without Flap Repair in Postoperative Defect Repair of Hypopharyngeal Carcinoma</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70131</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70131</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 17:06:13 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Zhiyan Lu; Dan li; Yi Fang; Yimiao Wang; Siyi Chen; Shuaichi Ma; Kexin Pang; Chen Zhao; Harry Hoang; Min Shu; Lei Cheng; Jian Chen; Haitao Wu; Peijie He</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70131</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70131</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background The reconstruction of hypopharyngeal tumor defect after tumorectomy is essential. Artificial materials play an important role in the case of extensive defects and a relative lack of healthy tissue. This study aims to investigate the role of acellular dermal matrix (ADM) in repairing defects following hypopharyngeal carcinoma resection. Methods A retrospective analysis was conducted on 280 patients with hypopharyngeal carcinoma. 143 patients accepted ADM‐assisted reconstruction while 137 patients didn't. Data on postoperative deglutition function, respiratory function, and complications were collected and analyzed. Results No immune rejection response was observed. In partial laryngectomy, ADM significantly induces the time for hospitalization, decannulation, and oral food intake compared to the control group ( p &lt; 0.05). In total laryngectomy, ADM has advantages in terms of the number of individuals with good deglutition function ( p &lt; 0.05). There is no significant difference in pharyngocutaneous fistula. Conclusions ADM is a promising biomaterial for reconstruction in hypopharyngeal carcinoma. It offers advantages such as a high success rate, good graft survival, accessibility, minimal immunogenicity, and simplified surgical procedures.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Intraoperatıve Nerve Monıtorıng Durıng Thyroıdectomy Can Reduce the Injury to the External Branch of the Superıor Laryngeal Nerve Durıng Superıor Thyroıd Pole Dıssectıon: A Prospective Randomized Study</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70128</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70128</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 17:05:21 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Nurcihan Aygun; Marika D. Russell; Kinyas Kartal; Adnan Isgor; Gregory W. Randolph; Mehmet Uludag</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70128</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70128</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background The primary aim of this study was to characterize the prevalence of external branch of the superior laryngeal nerve (EBSLN) injury with and without the use of intraoperative neuromonitoring (IONM) and identify factors associated with injury. Methods Patients referred to our clinic for thyroidectomy between June 2015 and June 2016 were prospectively randomized into two groups (single‐blinded): in Group 1, IONM was used during upper pole dissection only for the management of the recurrent laryngeal nerve (RLN); in Group 2, IONM was used for both RLN and EBSLN management. After thyroidectomy completion in all patients, cricothyroid muscle (CTM) EMG was performed. Results EBSLN injury was significantly higher in Group 1 (15.4 vs. 2.1% of NAR, p &lt; 0.001). EBSLN injury was detected in 23 (9.4%) of 245 Friedman type 1, in 7 (18.9%) of 37 Friedman type 2, and in 3 (3.2%) of 94 Friedman type 3 nerves. Conclusion EBSLN injury is often a transection injury associated with permanent EBSLN dysfunction. Use of IONM facilitates the prevention of EBSLN injury.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Chloride Intracellular Channel 2 Can Function as a Malignant Factor in Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70133</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70133</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Yuki Hosokawa; Shoko Miyoshi; Yuji Hayashi; Yuki Irifune; Eriko Sato; Sohei Mitani; Mohammed Choudhury; Hajime Yano; Junya Tanaka; Naohito Hato</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70133</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70133</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background The association of chloride intracellular channel 2 (CLIC2) with tumors has remained unclear. However, recently, CLIC2 was found to exhibit antitumor properties in some tumors. In this study, we aimed to evaluate the clinical relevance of CLIC2 expression in head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC) to determine whether it exerts antitumor effects similar to those in brain tumors and to explore its potential as a novel therapeutic target in HNSCC. Methods We explored the significance of CLIC in HNSCC using cell biological analyses and investigated the gene expression profile of the CLIC2 forced‐expressed HNSCC cell line. CLIC2 expression in human HNSCC was examined histopathologically. Results Forced expression of CLIC2 in HNSCC cells was accompanied by increased cell proliferation, resistance against natural killer cells, and expression of tumor‐promoting genes in addition to increased tumorigenicity upon xenografting in a mouse model. CLIC2 expression was observed in several human cases of HNSCC. Conclusion CLIC2 may act potentially as a novel risk factor for HNSCC.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Risk of Occult Contralateral Neck Metastasis in Early‐Stage HPV‐Related Lateralized Cancer of the Base of the Tongue</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70117</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70117</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 01:14:46 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Tyler R. Halle; Austin C. Cao; Anusha G. Naik; Gregory S. Weinstein; Jake J. Lee; Theodore A. Gobillot; Erin R. Kaye; Robert M. Brody; Devraj Basu; Bert W. O&apos;Malley; D. Gregory Farwell; Steven B. Cannady; Alexander Lin; John Lukens; Michelle Gentile; Jason G. Newman; Ara A. Chalian; Christopher H. Rasskeh; Karthik Rajasekaran</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70117</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70117</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Objectives (1) To determine the incidence of occult contralateral cervical lymph node metastasis in patients with early‐stage HPV‐associated base‐of‐tongue (BOT) oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma (OPSCC) treated with primary surgery; and (2) to compare survival and recurrence in patients who did and did not undergo contralateral neck treatment. Background Contralateral neck management in patients with early‐stage HPV+ OPSCC of the BOT treated surgically remains controversial. Despite lacking data, most patients receive surgery and/or radiation to the contralateral neck based on historical incidence of occult lymph node metastasis in OPSCC. Methods A retrospective chart review of patients with AJCC 7th edition pT1‐2, pN0‐1 HPV+ BOT OPSCC undergoing transoral robotic BOT resection and ipsilateral neck dissection with adjuvant treatment was conducted. The incidence of occult contralateral nodal metastasis was assessed. Overall and disease‐free survival were compared between patients who did and did not undergo contralateral neck treatment. Results Of 106 patients meeting inclusion criteria, 46 (43.3%) did not undergo treatment of the contralateral neck with radiation or lymphadenectomy, whereas 29 (27.4%) received radiation alone to the contralateral neck, and 31 (29.2%) underwent elective contralateral neck dissection without identification of occult metastasis in any case. Overall survival (HR: 0.95, 95% CI: 0.23–4.00) and disease‐free survival (HR: 1.43, CI: 0.55–3.71) did not significantly differ between patients who did and did not receive treatment to the contralateral neck. Conclusion Risk of occult contralateral cervical lymph node metastasis in patients with early‐stage HPV‐associated BOT OPSCC treated with primary surgery was low, prompting consideration of forgoing contralateral neck treatment in these patients.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Malignant Craniofacial Perivascular Epithelioid Cell Tumor: A Review of Literature With a Rare Presentation</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70126</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70126</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 01:10:57 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Jai Paris; Almater Abdullah; Terence Ang; Sarah Shepard; Dinesh Selva; Alkis J. Psaltis</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70126</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70126</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Perivascular epithelioid cell tumors (PEComas) are rare mesenchymal neoplasms with smooth muscle and melanocytic differentiation, typically occurring in genitourinary or abdominopelvic sites. While multiple anatomic sites have been reported, craniofacial involvement is exceptionally rare. Methods We report the first documented case of a probable high‐grade malignant PEComa of the sinonasal tract with anterior skull base and orbital extension. The patient was a 42‐year‐old woman with a germline RB1 mutation, prior radiotherapy for bilateral retinoblastoma as an infant, and a history of left‐sided sinonasal leiomyosarcoma treated with surgical resection and anthracycline chemotherapy. She represented six years later with new contralateral epistaxis and a friable right‐sided nasal mass. Upon endoscopy and imaging, a locally aggressive lesion was confirmed. Results Histopathology showed a highly proliferative tumor with immunohistochemistry positive for HMB45, melan‐A, SMA, caldesmon, and TFE3, with absent desmin and MITF. The lesion was most in keeping with a malignant PEComa. The tumor was resected via a combined transcranial, transcaruncular, and endoscopic endonasal approach, achieving clear margins. This case shows unusually rapid progression, likely influenced by prior radiation and germline RB1 gene mutation. Our literature review identified 41 previously reported primary craniofacial PEComas, consisting of 51% sinonasal, 37% orbital, and 10% skull base. Nearly all cases were benign and treated with surgical resection. Conclusions This report highlights a rare, malignant craniofacial PEComa with extensive invasion into the orbit and skull base, expanding the known clinical and molecular spectrum of these tumors.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Quantifying Neck Disability After Neck Dissection in HNSCC—A Prospective Study of Patient‐Reported and Objective Functional Outcomes</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70130</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70130</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 07:40:16 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Hongli Zhang; Fujiang Wang; Minjie Gu; Quanqing Wan; Rubao Guo; Lingling Duan; Mingbo Tian</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70130</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70130</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Neck dissection, a cornerstone of head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC) treatment, is associated with significant postoperative neck disability. This study prospectively evaluates the trajectory of patient‐reported and objective functional outcomes to quantify disability and identify key predictors. Methods A prospective cohort of 178 patients undergoing neck dissection for HNSCC was assessed preoperatively and at 3, 6, and 12 months postoperatively. The primary outcome was the change in the Neck Disability Index (NDI). Secondary outcomes included neck pain (Visual Analog Scale, VAS), patient‐specific function (Patient‐Specific Functional Scale, PSFS), cervical range of motion (CROM), manual muscle testing (MMT), and spinal accessory nerve (SAN) function. Results At 12 months, functional outcomes failed to return to preoperative baselines. A significant proportion of patients had severe neck disability (NDI &gt; 25, 22.7%) or poor objective neck mobility (CROM &lt; 70% normative, 26.7%). Radical neck dissection (RND vs. MRND/SND: OR = 2.10, 95% CI: 1.02–4.32), dissection involving levels IV/V (OR = 2.45, 95% CI: 1.11–5.39), and administration of chemotherapy (OR = 2.18, 95% CI: 1.02–4.66) were independent predictors of severe disability. The upper trapezius was the most affected muscle, with SAN function remaining impaired in 42% of patients at 12 months. Strong correlations were observed between subjective disability and objective measures like CROM ( r = −0.72, p &lt; 0.001) and trapezius strength ( r = −0.65, p &lt; 0.001). Conclusion Neck dissection results in persistent disability strongly linked to surgical extent and chemotherapy. The concordance between patient‐reported and objective measures underscores the need for integrated assessment and the development of tailored, multidisciplinary rehabilitation to mitigate long‐term morbidity.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Appraisal of Radiologic Size Criteria for Malignant Lymph Nodes in Parotid Region in Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma: Implication for Parotid‐Sparing IMRT</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70096</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70096</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 03:57:34 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Qiaojuan Guo; Xiaojing Yang; Zhiwei Yan; Xinlan Chen; Lisha Chen; Caizhu Pan; Jingfeng Zong; Hanchuan Xu; Yahan Zheng; Ziyi Wu; Youping Xiao; Jianji Pan; Shao Hui Huang; Shaojun Lin</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70096</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70096</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Purpose We evaluate the appropriateness of current radiology size criteria (short axial diameter, SAD ≥ 10 mm) for malignant nodes in the parotid region (PLN), and appreciate the clinical implications of the Node‐Reporting‐and‐Data‐System (Node‐RADS) in nasopharyngeal carcinoma (NPC). Methods and Material NPC patients who received curative IMRT were included. Pre‐treatment MRI was reviewed by two radiologists to record the presence/absence, size, and configuration of PLN, and calculated Node‐RADS score. Malignant PLN was defined as either fine‐needle aspiration (FNA) positive or the occurrence of subsequent out‐field in situ PLN failure following parotid‐sparing IMRT. Results Pre‐treatment PLN was identified in 74 (11.8%) of 627 consecutive patients. SAD PLNs were 5–6 mm ( n = 53, 72%), 6–8 mm ( n = 15, 20%), 8–10 mm ( n = 4, 5%), and ≥ 10 mm (2, 3%), respectively. FNAs were positive in 6 patients (2 each in SAD 6–8 mm, 8–10 mm, and ≥ 10 mm). Out‐field in situ PLN failure occurred in 6 patients: 1 with SAD 5–6 mm, 3 with SAD 6–8 mm, and 2 with SAD 8–10 mm. The risk of PLN being malignant was 1.9% (1/53), 33.3% (5/15), 100% (4/4), and 100% (2/2) in SAD 5–6 mm, 6–8 mm, 8–10 mm, and ≥ 10 mm subsets, respectively. Malignant PLN with Node‐RADS score ≥ 4 were 10% (1/10), 45.5% (5/11), and 100% (4/4) in SAD 5–6 mm, 6–8 mm, 8–10 mm subsets, respectively. Conclusion Current radiologic size criteria of ≥ 10 mm for positive PLN should be reduced to ≥ 8 mm. Node‐RADS score of 4–5, which includes adverse morphological nodal features, could improve the specificity of identifying malignant PLNs in the 6–8 mm subset.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Minimizing Chemoradiation Using a Surgical Algorithm for HPV‐Associated Cancer of Unknown Primary</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70124</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70124</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 01:09:15 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Georges E. Daoud; Andre J. Burnham; Nikhil T. Vettikattu; Nicole C. Schmitt; Brian J. Boyce; Jennifer H. Gross; Harry M. Baddour; Mark W. El‐Deiry; Conor E. Steuer; Nabil F. Saba; James E. Bates; William A. Stokes; Kelly R. Magliocca; Mihir R. Patel; Azeem S. Kaka</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70124</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70124</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background The majority of lesions originally diagnosed as cancer of unknown primary (CUP) are eventually identified as HPV‐associated oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma. Accurate primary tumor localization can facilitate targeted treatment or reduce adjuvant therapy. Methods This retrospective study examined patients who underwent transoral robotic surgery (TORS) for CUP from 2019 to 2022 at a tertiary care center. We analyzed the primary tumor identification rate, recurrence rate, and need for adjuvant therapy. Results A total of 48 patients with HPV‐associated CUP underwent TORS, achieving an 87.5% identification rate (42/48). A total of 39.5% (19/48) avoided direct radiation to the primary site, and 20.8% (10/48) received no radiation. No patients had local recurrence, though three experienced regional or distant recurrence. Conclusions A primary surgical approach to HPV‐associated CUP of the head and neck should be considered in every patient with CUP. When combined with a robust frozen section pathology protocol helping to guide intraoperative decision‐making and margin revision, and a multidisciplinary approach to adjuvant therapy, precise tumor localization can help appropriately direct adjuvant therapy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Disparities in Proton Radiation Utilization for HPV‐Associated Oropharyngeal Cancer Following TORS</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70122</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70122</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 22:20:26 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Jane Y. Tong; Vera Bzhilyanskaya; Jason K. Molitoris; Matthew J. Ferris; Kyle M. Hatten</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70122</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70122</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Introduction Racial, socioeconomic, and geographic disparities in receipt of proton radiation have been reported. Whether disparities exist for oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma (OPSCC) is not well studied. Methods Patients with HPV‐associated OPSCC treated with transoral robotic surgery (TORS) and adjuvant radiation from 2016 to 2023 were reviewed. Demographics, disease characteristics, treatment details, and socioeconomic variables were collected. Results Of 116 patients, 102 (87.9%) were male, 105 (90.5%) White, with a median age of 59.7 years. Fifty (43.1%) received proton radiation. Age, gender, race, tumor subsite, tumor and nodal staging, insurance, employment, and distance from our institution were not significantly associated with proton radiation, while higher median income was ( p = 0.04). Conclusion While higher median income was significantly associated with proton radiation, other traditionally described disparities were not apparent for HPV‐associated OPSCC treated with TORS. Although this cohort included predominantly privately insured White males, access to adjuvant proton therapy seemed to be equitably available across demographics.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Obstructive Sleep Apnea in Head and Neck Cancer Patients After Primary Treatment: A Review Focused on Oropharyngeal Cancer</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70098</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70098</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 01:44:37 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Nina Patel; Kennedy Johnson; Jolie Chang; Yi Cai; Patrick Ha; Ilya Likhterov</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70098</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70098</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Objective Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is a disorder with significant health implications. Variations in upper airway anatomy and pharyngeal tone are factors that predispose patients to OSA. Oropharyngeal cancer (OPC) may increase the risk of OSA due to treatment‐induced changes in the upper airway. This scoping review aims to assess the prevalence of OSA in OPC patients post‐treatment. Data Sources A search was conducted across multiple databases, including PubMed, Embase, and Cochrane Library, to identify studies reporting the prevalence of OSA in OPC patients post‐treatment (including surgery, radiation, and/or chemoradiation). Review Methods Studies were screened for eligibility by two reviewers. Inclusion criteria required studies to use standardized diagnostic criteria for OSA and provide prevalence data specifically for post‐treatment OPC patients. Results The search identified 788 studies: 30 underwent full‐text review, and 13 studies with 373 head and neck cancer (HNC) patients met inclusion criteria. The majority of studies did not disaggregate data for OPC from other subsites; one study provided sufficient data on OSA prevalence in OPC patients post‐treatment. Five studies reported AHI changes pre‐ and post‐treatment with a mean change of 5.4 events/h with only 2 studies reporting significant changes in OSA rates. Sleep‐related symptoms were captured in 11 studies with 2 comparing pre‐ and post‐treatment. Conclusion Despite the growing recognition of OSA as a potential comorbidity in cancer survivors, the literature does not adequately address the prevalence of OSA in OPC patients post‐treatment. This highlights the need for future studies targeting OSA prevalence in this population using standardized diagnostic methods and reporting criteria.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Longitudinal Patterns of Radiation‐Associated Dysphagia in Patients With Head and Neck Cancer: A Systematic Review</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70107</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70107</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 01:40:48 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Anuja H. Shah; Megan T. Nguyen; Shaun A. Nguyen; Justin C. Pelic; Kate Davidson; Ashli K. O&apos;Rourke</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70107</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70107</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Objective To investigate the diagnostic profile of early (i.e., &lt; 6 months of treatment) and late (i.e., ≥ 6 months of treatment) radiation‐associated dysphagia (RAD) in patients with head and neck cancer. Materials and Methods The literature was queried from inception to July 19, 2024. Outcomes included patient‐reported outcome measures, aspiration prevalence, pharyngoesophageal stricture rate, and gastric tube presence. Data were collected at various time points from baseline up to 24 months post‐treatment; longer‐term data beyond 24 months was descriptively summarized. Meta‐analysis of continuous measures (mean) and proportions (%) with 95% confidence intervals (CI) was performed. Results Of 2881 abstracts identified, 99 studies ( N = 15 578 patients) were included. Mean age was 58.4 years; 78.9% of patients were male. M.D. Anderson Dysphagia Inventory composite scores were 71.2 (CI: 66.8–75.6) at 3 months and 82.8 (CI: 79.2–86.3) at 24 months, signifying improvement in swallowing‐related quality of life. Aspiration prevalence was 28.4% (CI: 11.6–49.1) at 3 months and 8.8% (CI: 0.13–28.7) at 24 months. Stricture rate was 21.2% (CI: 9.7–15.2) at 6 months and 9.1% [CI: 3.0–17.9] at 24 months. Gastric tube presence declined from baseline (44.5% [CI: 36.8–52.4]) to 6 months (12.3% [CI: 9.7–16.6]) and fluctuated from 1 to 10 years post‐treatment (range: 4.14% [CI: 2.7–5.9] to 9.17% [CI: 5.5–14.2]). Conclusion RAD severity peaks within 3 months post‐treatment, with improvement by 6 months. However, even at 2 years post‐treatment, a substantial number of patients continue to experience clinically significant dysphagia. These findings highlight the persistent burden of RAD, underscoring the need for proactive longer‐term dysphagia evaluation and management in this population.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Hypofractionated Spot Scanning Proton Therapy for Head and Neck Mucosal Melanoma: A Retrospective Analysis With Quality‐of‐Life Outcome</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70121</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70121</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 03:21:17 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Koichiro Nakajima; Hiromitsu Iwata; Gaku Takano; Daiki Kojima; Yukiko Hattori; Yusuke Tsuzuki; Shuou Sudo; Kensuke Hayashi; Toshiyuki Toshito; Hideo Fukano; Hiroyuki Ogino; Akio Hiwatashi</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70121</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70121</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Objective To evaluate clinical outcomes and quality of life (QOL) following hypofractionated spot‐scanning proton therapy (SSPT) for head and neck malignant mucosal melanoma (HNMM). Methods This retrospective study included 39 patients treated with SSPT (60–64 Gy[RBE] in 15–16 fractions) between 2013 and 2023. Endpoints included overall survival (OS), local control (LC), progression‐free survival (PFS), toxicities, and QOL. Results Most tumors were located in the sinonasal cavity ( n = 32). Surgery was performed in 8 patients; 19 received immune checkpoint inhibitors post‐SSPT. The 3‐year OS, LC, and PFS were 50%, 83%, and 30%, respectively. Larger tumor volumes (≥ 20 cm 3 ) were linked to worse PFS. Grade 3 mucositis occurred in 13%. Late toxicities included sinus disorder, osteonecrosis, and blindness (3%–5%). QOL was largely preserved, with notable declines in pain, swallowing, and mouth opening. Conclusion SSPT provides favorable LC with acceptable toxicity. Effective systemic therapies are needed to improve long‐term outcomes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Oral Carcinoma Cuniculatum: A Rare, Clinically Challenging Entity—A Case Report and Updated Systematic Review</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70111</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70111</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 01:39:28 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Po‐Jung Huang; Ching‐Heng Ting; Yi‐Shing Leu; Nien‐Hsuan Ho; Chien‐Fu Lin</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70111</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70111</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Oral carcinoma cuniculatum (OCC) is a rare, well‐differentiated variant of oral squamous cell carcinoma (SCC) that often mimics benign lesions, resulting in delayed diagnosis. Evidence on its clinical behavior and risk of recurrence remains limited. Methods We report a representative OCC case and conducted a PRISMA‐based systematic review of PubMed, Embase, Cochrane Library, Google Scholar, and Airiti Library, including studies with patient‐level data. Results Forty‐six studies comprising 115 patients were included. The gingiva was the most common primary site. Nodal metastasis was reported in 9.0% (8/89), and the overall recurrence rate was 15.8%, predominantly local. Higher recurrences were found among patients receiving neck dissection or adjuvant therapy, which likely reflected selection bias rather than a treatment effect. Conclusions OCC shows a low nodal metastatic rate and mainly local recurrence. Routine elective neck dissection may not be required in clinically N0 patients, but this hypothesis requires validation in larger, multi‐institutional cohorts.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Radiotherapy Outcomes and Prognostic Factors in Head and Neck NUT Carcinoma: A Single‐Center Cohort Analysis</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70119</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70119</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 01:36:46 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Zhuomiao Ye; Helei Yan; Xin Li; Dan Yang; Fei Xie; Chao Deng; Mingzhu Yin</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70119</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70119</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background NUT carcinoma is a rare, aggressive malignancy defined by NUTM1 gene rearrangement, with the head and neck as the second most common site. Its prognosis is poor, and current treatment references other cancers. Although radiotherapy is key in managing head and neck tumors, its efficacy and prognostic factors in head and neck NUT carcinoma are unclear. Methods We retrospectively analyzed 31 patients with locally advanced or recurrent/metastatic head and neck NUT carcinoma treated with radiotherapy. OS and PFS were estimated by Kaplan–Meier, and prognostic factors were identified using Cox regression. Results Among 31 patients (64.5% male, median age 37), nasal cavity/paranasal sinuses were the most common primary site (51.6%). Most received intensity‐modulated radiotherapy with ≥ 66 Gy. Median OS and PFS were 18.73 and 3 months, respectively. Nasal cavity/paranasal sinus primaries had the worst prognosis (median OS: 16.7 months). Locally advanced cases had significantly better survival than recurrent/metastatic disease (median OS: 30.43 vs. 13.93 months; PFS: 5.83 vs. 2.3 months). High‐dose radiotherapy (≥ 66 Gy) was associated with improved OS, and R0 resection combined with ≥ 66 Gy achieved median OS of 27.9 months. In surgical patients, GTV longest diameter &gt; 3.5 cm independently predicted worse PFS (HR = 5.01, p = 0.01). Recurrent/metastatic status was the most critical independent adverse prognostic factor for both PFS (HR = 4.56) and OS (HR = 10.12). Adjuvant therapy after radiotherapy prolonged PFS, particularly in locally advanced patients. BETi‐based regimens before radiotherapy showed potential for improved locoregional and distant control in postoperative recurrence/metastasis. Conclusions Prognosis in head and neck NUT carcinoma treated with radiotherapy is affected by disease status, primary site, radiotherapy dose, and adjuvant therapy. Locally advanced patients benefit most from high‐dose radiotherapy and adjuvant therapy. GTV &gt; 3.5 cm identifies high‐risk populations requiring intensified treatment, while BETi may improve outcomes in postoperative recurrence/metastasis.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Modified Platysma Myocutaneous Flap Reconstruction for Advanced Laryngeal Carcinoma: A Multicenter Retrospective Cohort Study</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70120</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70120</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 21:10:30 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Zhen Jiang; Pengwei Zhao; Zheng Jiang; Jun Liu; Xinliang Pan</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70120</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70120</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background This study presents a modified platysma myocutaneous flap technique for reconstructing extensive laryngeal defects in patients with advanced‐stage transglottic laryngeal carcinoma. Methods A retrospective cohort analysis was conducted on patients undergoing organ‐preserving partial laryngectomy followed by reconstruction using a modified platysma flap. Primary endpoints included decannulation rate and 3‐year overall survival. Functional recovery of respiration, swallowing, and phonation was evaluated using validated scales. Results Sixty patients (mean age: 62.85 ± 6.09 years) were enrolled across two centers. The overall decannulation rate was 85.0%, with significantly higher success rates observed in the partial laryngectomy group ( p &lt; 0.05). The 3‐year survival rate was 78.3%. Swallowing and phonatory functions were well preserved, with median scores of 2 and 1, respectively. The technique was associated with a low incidence of flap‐related complications (13.3%) and favorable mucosalization outcomes. Conclusion The modified platysma flap offers a practical and effective reconstructive strategy for laryngeal defects in advanced carcinoma, achieving satisfactory respiratory decannulation and preservation of laryngeal function with minimal morbidity.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Postoperative Adjuvant Therapy in Resectable Advanced Oral Squamous Cell Carcinoma With Intermediate Risk Factors</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70106</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70106</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 01:47:20 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Koichi Koizumi; Fumitaka Obayashi; Mirai Higaki; Kota Morishita; Atsuko Hamada; Sachiko Yamasaki; Nanako Ito; Souichi Yanamoto</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70106</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70106</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Postoperative adjuvant therapy strategies are generally determined based on pathological risk stratification in oral cancer. However, the efficacy of postoperative adjuvant therapy in patients with intermediate‐risk factors for recurrence of oral cancer such as close surgical margins, pT3–T4 classification, pN2–N3 nodal status, perineural invasion, vascular invasion, lymphatic invasion and pattern of invasion remains unclear, and no standardized treatment guidelines or consensus have been established to date. Therefore, this study retrospectively analyzed the clinical significance of risk factors for pathological recurrence in patients with advanced oral cancer and evaluated the impact of postoperative adjuvant therapy on patient prognosis. Methods This retrospective clinical study included 130 patients who underwent initial radical surgical resection for advanced oral squamous cell carcinoma (OSCC) at our institution between January 2010 and December 2023. The postoperative recurrence risk factors included ENE of the cervical lymph nodes, positive surgical margins, close surgical margins, pathological T classification (pT3 or pT4), pathological N classification (pN2 or pN3), metastasis to level IV or V lymph nodes, perineural invasion, vascular invasion, and lymphatic invasion. We analyzed the relationships among the presence of these risk factors, administration of postoperative adjuvant therapy (RT or CRT), occurrence of recurrence or metastasis, and patient prognosis (DFS). Results Patients with lymphatic invasion had a significantly lower survival rate than those without lymphatic invasion (66.7% vs. 82.8%, p &lt; 0.05). Although pT4, pN2–N3, perineural invasion‐positive and vascular invasion‐positive did not reach statistical significance, a trend toward reduced survival was observed in each case. The perineural invasion‐positive group had significantly higher recurrence and metastasis rates than the perineural invasion‐negative group (51.9% vs. 23.6%, p &lt; 0.05). Multivariate analysis using logistic regression also confirmed the presence of perineural invasion as an independent prognostic factor (HR = 4.496, p = 0.019). Conclusions This study demonstrated that perineural invasion is a significant risk factor for recurrence and that lymphatic invasion is a poor prognostic factor in oral cancer. Postoperative adjuvant therapy in patients with perineural or lymphatic invasion‐positive disease contributed to reduced recurrence rates and prolonged survival. These findings suggest that the pathological evaluation of perineural and lymphatic invasions is an important indicator in determining the appropriateness of postoperative adjuvant therapy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Myopericytoma of the Head and Neck: A Case Series and Literature Review</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70113</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70113</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 01:49:45 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Peter S. Giannaris; Matthew Mendelsohn; Mostafa Kokabee; Shengjie Cui; Dominick Guerrero; Mark Chaskes; Judd Fastenberg; Charles C. L. Tong</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70113</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70113</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Myopericytoma (MPC) is a rare perivascular tumor with myoid differentiation that poses diagnostic and therapeutic challenges in the head and neck. Methods We present four cases of oral and sinonasal MPC and conducted a literature review to analyze clinical characteristics, diagnostic approaches, and management. Results Sixty‐five published cases were identified, yielding a cohort of 69 patients. The oral cavity was the most common site (44.9%) followed by parotid (15.9%), sinonasal (10.1%), neck (10.1%), and other head regions (18.8%). Complete excision was achieved in 95.7% of cases with a 7.2% recurrence rate. Histopathology confirmed MPC in all cases with characteristic perivascular spindle cell proliferation, 95.6% showing positive smooth muscle actin immunostaining. Conclusion MPC must be considered in the differential diagnosis of vascular head and neck lesions. Complete surgical excision with negative margins remains the treatment of choice, with immunohistochemistry essential for accurate diagnosis.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Potential Utility of Micronucleus and Binucleus Frequencies in Malignancy Prediction in Thyroid Nodules</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70110</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70110</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 01:32:30 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Hilmi Alper; Makbule Nihan Somuncu; Rukiye Erdem Özçelik; Fakih Cihat Eravcı; Ayşe Gül Zamani; Hamdi Arbağ</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70110</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70110</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Objective To investigate the frequency of micronuclei (MN) and binucleated (BN) cells in thyroid nodules and adjacent normal tissue, and evaluate their correlation with cytological (Bethesda classification) and histopathological diagnoses to assess their potential utility in preoperative malignancy prediction. Methods This prospective study included 39 patients (16 benign, 19 papillary carcinoma, 4 follicular carcinoma) who underwent thyroidectomy. Tissue samples from both nodular and adjacent normal thyroid regions were collected. MN and BN frequencies were evaluated in 1000 cells per sample using May‐Grünwald and 5% Giemsa staining. Data were analyzed in relation to Bethesda categories and final surgical pathology using mixed‐effects models in R 4.4.1. ROC analysis was conducted to assess the diagnostic performance of MN/BN frequency. Results MN and BN frequencies were significantly higher in nodular tissue compared to adjacent normal thyroid tissue ( p &lt; 0.05). Malignant lesions showed significantly increased MN/BN frequencies compared to benign ones, although no significant difference was observed between papillary and follicular subtypes ( p &lt; 0.05). MN/BN frequencies were also significantly higher in Bethesda categories III–VI compared to categories I–II ( p &lt; 0.05). No significant variation was found in normal thyroid tissue across cytological or pathological groups. Conclusion MN and BN cell frequencies were elevated in malignant nodules and higher Bethesda categories, supporting their potential role as adjunctive cytogenetic markers in thyroid nodule assessment. While findings are promising, their diagnostic utility in indeterminate nodules remains unclear. Larger, FNAB‐based studies are required to validate their feasibility and clinical relevance in routine preoperative evaluation.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Neck Spasms After Lateral Neck Dissection: A Survey of Head and Neck Cancer Patients</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70108</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70108</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 03:10:23 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Kelly Bridgham; Teresa Duong; Praneet Kaki; Tyler Allcroft; Kalena Liu; Eric Mastrolonardo; Hannah Kenny; Emma De Ravin; Arielle Thal; Joseph Curry</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70108</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70108</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Neck spasms or myoclonus are an underreported sequela of HNC treatment, often described following radiation. The frequency of neck spasm following neck dissection is unknown. Methods A phone survey was conducted of HNC patients following neck dissection to determine the incidence and severity of neck spasms using the Penn Spasm Frequency Scale and Neck Dissection Impairment Index. Demographic and treatment‐related factors were compared between those with and without neck spasms. Results 56/136 patients (41.2%) responded with 16 (28.6%) reporting neck spasms. Spasms ranged from mild to severe and were associated with a lower NDII score (85.62 vs. 90.44, p = 0.078) Neck spasms occurred irrespective of shoulder dysfunction due to cranial nerve 11 injury and were not associated with any patient or treatment‐related factors, including radiation therapy. Conclusions Neck spasms occur after neck dissection irrespective of radiation therapy or spinal accessory nerve injury with a negative impact on quality of life.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Anti‐Thyroglobulin Antibody Trajectory and Risk of Structural Recurrence in Patients With Papillary Thyroid Cancer</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70109</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70109</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 01:44:46 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Hongxi Wang; Tian Tian; Qianrui Li; Rong Tian</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70109</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70109</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background To explore the relationship between anti‐thyroglobulin antibody (TgAb) trajectories and recurrence risk in papillary thyroid cancer (PTC) patients. Methods This multiple‐center, retrospective cohort included 4161 patients who had no evidence of structural disease and a stimulated thyroglobulin (s‐Tg) of ≤ 10 ng/mL at the initial radioiodine (RAI) treatment. Among 3660 patients who had repeated TgAb measurements (before RAI treatment, 1, 6, or 12 months after treatment) and available response assessments, latent class models were used to identify TgAb trajectories. Associations of trajectories with the risk of recurrence were estimated. Results Four distinct TgAb trajectories were identified. Compared with patients belonging to the consistently negative trajectory, patients with the other three trajectories had higher risks of recurrence (medium‐level descent: odds ratio = 3.46 [95% CI = 1.56–6.90], high‐level descent: 8.04 [1.26–28.78], persistently increasing: 12.11 [5.73–23.75]). Conclusions TgAb trajectories within 1 year after RAI treatment are associated with the risk of recurrence in PTC patients with a s‐Tg ≤ 10 ng/mL. Trial Registration Registered at www.chictr.org.cn (identifier: ChiCTR2300075574)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Preoperative Anxiety and Depression Symptoms Stratifying Based on Gender Differences Influence Outcome of Oral Squamous Cell Carcinoma</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70105</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70105</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 23:26:01 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Lirui Zhang; Chang Liu; Qiaoshi Xu; Chong Wang; Bo Li; Huan Liu; Hao Wang; Zhien Feng</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70105</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70105</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background The objective of this study is to investigate the impact of preoperative anxiety symptoms (AS) and depression symptoms (DS) on clinical outcomes and time to treatment initiation (TTI) of oral squamous cell carcinoma (OSCC). Methods Seven hundred and twenty‐five OSCC patients were included. Kaplan–Meier and Cox models analyzed hazard ratio (HR) for survival, while accelerated failure time models estimated time ratio (TR) for TTI. Results Females showed higher prevalence and severity of AS ( p = 0.014) and DS ( p = 0.002). Mild AS (HR: 2.132, 95% CI: 1.091–4.165; p = 0.027) and DS (HR: 2.061, 95% CI: 1.052–4.038; p = 0.035) increased mortality risk in females. Mild DS prolonged TTI in females (TR: 1.450, 95% CI: 1.001–2.099; p = 0.049). Males with mild DS (TR: 0.718, 95% CI: 0.549–0.940; p = 0.016) or moderate–severe AS (TR: 0.562, 95% CI: 0.382–0.826; p = 0.003) had reduced TTI. Conclusions Psychological distress impacts survival and TTI differently by gender.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Tracheostomy in Flap‐Based Head and Neck Cancer Surgery: A Meta‐Analysis of Indications and Adverse Outcomes</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70102</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70102</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 23:54:46 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Raisa Chowdhury; Khanh Linh Tran; Naser Karimi; Jhorrit Kahlon; Cornelius Kürten; Sena Turkdogan; Eitan Prisman</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70102</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70102</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Tracheostomy is frequently performed during flap‐based reconstruction for head and neck cancer, but predictive factors and complications are not well established. Methods A systematic review and meta‐analysis was conducted per PRISMA guidelines. Studies of adult patients undergoing free or pedicled flap reconstruction were included. Pooled tracheostomy rates, predictors, and complications were analyzed using random‐effects models. Heterogeneity was assessed with the I 2 statistic. Results Twenty‐six studies (27 029 patients) were included. The pooled tracheostomy rate was 54.6%, decreasing to 42.4% when routine tracheostomy studies were excluded. Advanced tumor stage, oropharyngeal site, bilateral neck dissection, prior radiotherapy, and smoking predicted tracheostomy. Flap type was not significantly associated. The overall complication rate was 16.3%, including airway issues (2.6%). No significant change in tracheostomy rates was observed over 30 years. Conclusions Tracheostomy use is influenced by tumor, surgical, and patient factors. Selective tracheostomy and validated risk tools may improve outcomes. Further prospective studies are needed.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Fully COVID‐19 Vaccinated Status Enhanced the Efficacy of Immune Checkpoint Inhibitors in Patients With Recurrent or Metastatic Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70104</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70104</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 22:48:59 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Chien‐Chung Wang; Chih‐Chun Wang; Chuan‐Chien Yang; Tzer‐Zen Hwang; Ching‐Feng Lien; Yu‐Chen Shih; Shyh‐An Yeh; Meng‐Che Hsieh</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70104</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70104</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Little is known regarding the interaction between vaccination and immunotherapy in cancer patients. Herein, we conducted a retrospective study to evaluate the impact of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID‐19) vaccinated status on survival in patients with recurrent or metastatic head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (R/M HNSCC) treated with immune checkpoint inhibitors (ICI). Methods Patients who were treated with ICI for their R/M HNSCC were reviewed retrospectively. Patients who received at least one shot of the vaccine against COVID‐19 were recruited into our study. Patients were stratified into fully vaccinated (FV) and partially vaccinated (PV) according to their vaccination status. Kaplan–Meier curves were estimated for progression‐free survival (PFS) and overall survival (OS). Results A total of 127 patients were enrolled in our study for oncologic outcomes evaluation, including 70 FV and 57 PV. For the total population, the median PFS was 4.6 months and OS was 23.7 months. After stratifying according to COVID‐19 vaccination status, the median PFS was 6.2 months in FV and 3.1 months in PV ( p = 0.010). The median OS was 32.5 months in FV and 10.3 months in PV ( p &lt; 0.001). After the last dose of vaccination, the median neutrophil‐lymphocyte ratio and platelet‐lymphocyte ratio were significantly lower in FV than in PV ( p &lt; 0.001). No new safety issues were found in our patient cohort and were insignificant between the FV and PV groups. Conclusions R/M HNSCC patients with FV had significantly lower NLR and PLR, and had better survival when treated with ICI without increasing treatment toxicity.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Transoral Robotic Surgery (TORS) for Head and Neck Cancer in the Elderly Population: Functional Outcomes, Survival, and Complications</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70097</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70097</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 02:58:14 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Erim Pamuk; Avinash Beharry; Karma Lambercy; Margaux Dalla‐Vale; Nina Wahler; Şefik Hoşal; Christian Simon</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70097</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70097</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Objective To compare functional and oncologic outcomes in elderly (≥ 70 years) and nonelderly (&lt; 70 years) patients after transoral robotic surgery (TORS). Methods A retrospective chart review was conducted on 114 patients who underwent TORS for head and neck squamous cell carcinoma between 2012 and 2022. Patient and tumor characteristics, perioperative details, complications, and survival parameters were analyzed. Swallowing function was assessed using the Functional Outcome Swallowing Scale (FOSS). Results Of the 114 patients, 37 (32.5%) were elderly, and 77 (67.5%) were nonelderly. Elderly patients had higher comorbidity scores ( p &lt; 0.001). Oropharyngeal and oral cavity primaries were more common in the nonelderly group, whereas laryngeal primaries predominated in elderly patients ( p &lt; 0.01). Complication rates were higher in nonelderly (37.6%) than in elderly (18.9%) patients, though not statistically significant ( p = 0.07). In elderly patients, FOSS scores showed no significant change preoperatively, postoperatively (&lt; 3 months), or at the last follow‐up (median 36 months). The nonelderly group experienced worse early postoperative FOSS scores compared to baseline but showed significant improvement, returning to preoperative levels by the last follow‐up. Nonelderly patients had better FOSS scores at last follow‐up compared to elderly patients ( p = 0.014). Overall and recurrence‐free survival outcomes were better in the nonelderly group, but disease‐specific survival rates were comparable. Conclusion Despite higher comorbidity rates in the elderly, TORS demonstrated favorable complication rates in the elderly population. Swallowing function returned to baseline after 3 months in both groups. TORS appears safe for elderly patients with comparable oncologic outcomes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Geriatric Nutritional Risk Index Predicts Treatment Intolerance and Survival in Head and Neck Cancer</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70101</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70101</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 02:44:35 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Raisa Chowdhury; Alex M. Mlynarek; Keith Richardson; Nader Sadeghi; Michael P. Hier; Sabrina Wurzba; Khashayar Esfahani; Nathaniel Bouganim; Khalil Sultanem; George Shenouda; Christina Tsien; Marco A. Mascarella</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70101</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70101</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Malnutrition is associated with worse outcomes in head and neck cancer (HNC). The geriatric nutritional risk index (GNRI) may predict postoperative morbidity and survival, but its role remains underexplored. Methods An ambispective study of patients undergoing HNC surgery at two academic centers (2015–2024) was performed. Preoperative GNRI was categorized into moderate‐to‐high risk (&lt; 92), low risk (92–98), and no risk (&gt; 98). Outcomes included 90‐day mortality, treatment intolerance, overall survival, and disease‐free survival. Analyses were performed using multivariable logistic and Cox regression adjusted for age, Charlson Comorbidity Index (CCI), tumor stage, primary tumor site, and percutaneous endoscopic gastrostomy (PEG) status. Patients with prior head and neck cancer or prior radiation were excluded. Results Among 312 treatment‐naïve surgical patients, 13% were moderate‐to‐high GNRI risk and 8% low risk. Moderate‐to‐high GNRI risk had higher major adverse events (57% vs. 36% in no‐risk), greater treatment intolerance (61% vs. 41%), and a trend toward higher 90‐day mortality (11% vs. 4%). On multivariable models adjusted for tumor site and pathologic stage, moderate‐to‐high GNRI risk was associated with higher odds of 90‐day mortality (OR 2.99, 95% CI 1.01–9.31; p = 0.048) and treatment intolerance (OR 2.35, 95% CI 1.21–4.56; p = 0.012). Cox regression showed shorter overall (HR 2.28, 95% CI 1.44–3.62; p &lt; 0.001) and disease‐free survival (HR 1.87, 95% CI 1.20–2.91; p = 0.005). Conclusions The GNRI predicted treatment intolerance and poorer survival in patients with operable HNC.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Sclerotic Head and Neck Paragangliomas: An Unfavorable Indicator Associated With Surgical Outcomes</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70049</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70049</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 02:14:19 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Chenliang Yao; Dingfang Cao; Yaru Feng; Yiming Ding; Jing Zhou; Zhigang Huang; Yingshi Piao; Zhengya Yu; Xiaohong Chen</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70049</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70049</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background This retrospective case–control study investigated surgical outcomes of head and neck paragangliomas (HNPGLs) with varying degrees of sclerosis. Methods Data from 95 patients who underwent HNPGL surgery over 20 years were analyzed. Based on histology, tumors were classified as having non‐significant (&lt; 30%) or significant (≥ 30%) sclerosis. Results Seventy patients had non‐significant sclerosis and 25 had significant sclerosis. The significant sclerosis group was younger (39 vs. 44 years, p = 0.026), had more multiple tumors (48% vs. 12.9%, p = 0.001), higher nerve injury rates ( p = 0.021), and more vascular injuries (20.8% vs. 4.17%, p = 0.022). Multivariate analysis identified tumor volume (OR = 1.014, p = 0.005) and sclerosis degree (OR = 0.276, p = 0.013) as independent risk factors for severe complications involving both nerve and vascular injury. Conclusion Sclerotic HNPGLs are associated with earlier onset, multiple tumors, and increased risk of intraoperative complications, suggesting unfavorable surgical outcomes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Dental Rehabilitation After Bone Mandibular Reconstruction for Head and Neck Cancer: A GETTEC Multicenter Study</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70090</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70090</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Roussel Lise‐Marie; Elaldi Roxane; Anquetil Marine; Lévêque Emilie; Babin Emmanuel; Bozec Alexandre; Lasne Cardon Audrey; Boulay Alexandre; Le Guyader Maud; Thureau Sébastien; Brenet Esteban; Clatot Florian</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70090</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70090</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background The microvascular bone free flap (MBFF) is the preferred reconstruction after mandibular resection as it facilitates secondary dental rehabilitation. Methods In this multicenter study, patients were included if treated between January 2017 and January 2022 for head and neck cancer with MBFF reconstruction. Results Of the 487 identified patients, 104 patients were included. Median follow‐up was 49 months. 61 patients (59%) had no dental rehabilitation. Of the 43 rehabilitated patients, 81% had a conventional prosthesis and 19% an implant‐supported prosthesis. Neither the number of osteotomies, nor the complexity of the reconstruction, nor the radiotherapy, were statistically associated with dental rehabilitation. Only the absence of a dental specialist in the center ( p = 0.04) and a number of one or fewer native mandibular teeth ( p = 0.05) were significantly associated with no dental rehabilitation in multivariate analysis. Conclusion The rate of dental rehabilitation is still insufficient. The presence of a dental specialist is essential.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Computer‐Assisted Versus Freehand Surgery in Oncological Margins Control for Oral Squamous Cell Carcinomas: A Retrospective Case‐Control Clinical Study</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70095</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70095</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 04:29:19 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Alice Marzi Manfroni; Otto Pietro Scaccini; Francesco Ceccariglia; Giulia Querzoli; Anna Caterina Leucci; Laura Cercenelli; Emanuela Marcelli; Maria Pia Foschini; Giovanni Badiali; Achille Tarsitano</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70095</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70095</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Margin control is a crucial prognostic factor in head and neck oncological surgery. This retrospective case‐control study aims to assess the superiority of computer‐assisted surgery compared to traditional surgery in achieving optimal resection margins in maxillofacial oncologic surgery. Methods Eighty patients with stage T3 or T4 oral squamous cell carcinoma were included, equally divided into computer‐assisted surgery (CAS) and freehand groups. Negative, close, and positive margin rates were compared. Logistic regression with Firth's correction and multivariable Cox models for disease‐free survival (DFS) and overall survival (OS) were applied, with tobacco and alcohol included as covariates. Sensitivity analyses used inverse probability of treatment weighting (IPTW)‐weighted models. Results CAS was associated with a significantly lower risk of positive margins (OR 0.24; 95% CI: 0.06–0.78; p = 0.01), confirmed in the IPTW analysis. DFS was significantly improved with CAS in both multivariable and IPTW Cox models (HR 0.41 and 0.46, respectively), while OS showed no significant benefit. Nodal status emerged as the strongest prognostic factor. Conclusions Despite its univocality, the CAS technology seems to offer significant advantages in achieving precise oncological margin control for oral squamous cell carcinomas.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Regional Osteocutaneous Submental Island Flap for Premaxillary Reconstruction: A Clinical Experience</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70099</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70099</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 01:50:31 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Ebrahim Karimi; Pooria Mousavi; Ali Yousefzadeh; Niloufar Saeedi; Farbood Farahbakhsh; Mahdieh Mohebbi; Kayvan Aghazadeh; Farrokh Heidari</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70099</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70099</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Reconstruction of premaxillary defects remains a surgical challenge due to the region's functional and aesthetic importance. While prosthetic rehabilitation and osteocutaneous free flaps are commonly used, they can be resource‐intensive or unsuitable for some patients. This study reports our experience using the regional osteocutaneous submental island flap (ROC‐SIF) for premaxillary reconstruction. Methods We retrospectively reviewed four patients with premaxillary defects who underwent reconstruction using ROC‐SIF between 2017 and 2022. All patients had malignant tumors with no clinical or radiologic evidence of cervical lymph node involvement (N0). Flap harvest technique, intraoperative findings, and postoperative outcomes were analyzed. Results Defect sizes ranged from 30 to 58 mm. ROC‐SIF provided adequate soft tissue coverage and bony support for all cases. Functional outcomes, including speech and swallowing, were acceptable. Aesthetic results were satisfactory to both patients and surgeons. No major flap‐related complications occurred. Donor site morbidity was minimal. However, the narrow diameter of the bony component limited its suitability for dental implantation. Conclusion ROC‐SIF is a reliable, cost‐effective option for the reconstruction of small to moderate premaxillary defects, particularly in settings where free flap reconstruction is contraindicated or unavailable. Its straightforward harvest, minimal morbidity, and satisfactory functional and aesthetic outcomes make it a viable alternative in selected patients. Further studies with larger cohorts are warranted to better define its role and limitations in oral cavity reconstruction.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Genomic and Immune Correlates of EZH2 Expression and Activity in Olfactory Neuroblastoma</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70076</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70076</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Elisabetta Xue; Tolulope Adeyelu; Harris Krause; Andrew Elliott; Ranee Mehra; Heloisa Soares; Emil Lou; Ari Vanderwalde; David Spetzler; Dara Bracken‐Clarke; Nyall R. London; James L. Gulley; Charalampos S. Floudas</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70076</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70076</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Purpose Olfactory neuroblastoma (ONB) is a rare sinonasal malignancy with limited therapeutic options in the recurrent/metastatic setting; little is known regarding its responsiveness to immunotherapy. Inhibition of enhancer of zeste homolog 2 (EZH2) has been shown to improve T‐cell‐mediated killing and susceptibility to immune checkpoint inhibitors in a variety of cancers. We aimed to evaluate the expression and activity of EZH2 in ONB and its association with immune characteristics. Materials and Methods We studied a cohort of 36 ONB real‐world patient samples that underwent molecular profiling at a centralized lab (Caris Life Science). To infer EZH2 methyltransferase activity, we adopted an EZH2 gene repression signature (ERS) score: ONB samples were stratified into ERS‐low and ERS‐high subgroups, corresponding to high and low inferred EZH2 methyltransferase activity, respectively. Transcriptomic data were utilized to calculate the T‐cell‐inflamed (TCI) score and mitogen‐activated protein kinase (MAPK) pathway activation score (MPAS). Tumor immune microenvironment composition was inferred from tumor‐derived bulk RNA sequencing data. We analyzed immunologic differences between ERS‐low and ERS‐high ONB. Results In ERS‐high ONB, we observed a higher expression of immune‐related genes, a higher proportion of TCI tumors, and an enrichment in inflammatory pathways. ERS‐high ONB also displayed increased macrophages, and to a lesser extent, B cells and CD8 + T cell infiltration in the tumor microenvironment. Also, ERS‐high was associated with increased MPAS, potentially identifying ONB with increased susceptibility to MAPK inhibitors. These data were confirmed in an independent validation cohort using a publicly available dataset. Conclusions Taken together, our data suggest that low EZH2 activity is associated with a more immunogenic microenvironment, paving the way for potential combinations of EZH2 inhibitors with checkpoint blockade in ONB.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>An Isolated Soft Tissue Ectopic Paraganglioma in the Head and Neck</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70093</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70093</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 02:27:02 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Salmaan Sayeed; Luke Stanisce; Ricardo J. Ramirez; Soo Yeon Sohn; Azita Khorsandi; Mark L. Urken</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70093</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70093</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Paragangliomas are rare neuroendocrine tumors derived from autonomic paraganglia of neural crest origin. While typically found at predictable sites in the head and neck, ectopic paragangliomas in unusual locations are exceptionally rare and diagnostically challenging. Methods We describe a novel presentation of an ectopic paraganglioma found as a discrete soft tissue mass in the neck. Results A 45‐year‐old female with a pathogenic mutation in the SDHB gene was diagnosed with an isolated ectopic paraganglioma in left level III. Intraoperatively, the soft tissue mass was anatomically separate from the carotid sheath and all thyroid and laryngeal neurovascular structures. Histopathology revealed the absence of lymph node architecture, excluding the diagnosis of metastasis. Conclusions This case represents a previously unreported location of an ectopic head and neck paraganglioma, unrelated to known neurovascular structures or nodal metastasis, highlighting key diagnostic and management considerations—especially in the context of hereditary disease.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Quality of Life After Surgical Treatment of Head and Neck Paragangliomas</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70084</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70084</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 01:56:14 -0800</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Christina Sauter; Philipp Erhart; Dittmar Böckler; Patrick Schuler; Peter K. Plinkert; Ralph Hohenberger</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70084</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70084</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Head and neck paragangliomas (HNPGLs) are rare neuroendocrine tumors and often arise in the head and neck. Due to their localization, the tumor and its surgical treatment pose a risk for cranial nerve impairments. Few studies have focused on the health‐related quality of life (HRQOL) in patients with HNPGLs and their relation to tumor localization. Methods In patients ( n = 125) treated with primary surgery for HNPGLs between 2006 and 2023, clinical data was obtained. Long‐term QOL was assessed with the validated German version of the EORTC QLQ‐H&amp;N43 with a mean follow‐up since surgery of 6.0 years. Results Most common were carotid body PGLs ( n = 78; 62.4%) including Shamblin I ( n = 25), II ( n = 42) and III ( n = 9) along jugular ( n = 31; 24.8%) and vagal ( n = 10; 8.0%) tumors. In the QLQ‐H&amp;N43, the scales fear of progression (41.2), coughing (33.9), neurological problems (22.4), sexuality (21.4), and swallowing (21.2) showed the highest mean scores. Jugular and vagal tumors showed higher symptom levels compared to carotid body tumors, especially Shamblin I. Conclusions Surgical treatment of PGLs may lead to significant impairments in physical and psychological domains, especially in larger carotid body, vagal and jugular tumors. Structured pre‐ and postoperative cranial nerve examinations and interprofessional support should be provided to mitigate postoperative QOL reduction.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Study on the Ultrasonic Characteristics of the Paraglottic Space at the Glottic Level in Normal Adults</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70050</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70050</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 23:11:22 -0700</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Xiang‐ru Wang; Hua Wang; Yue Gao; Guo Chen; Xiao‐peng Li; Lei Sun</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70050</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70050</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Objective High‐frequency ultrasound was used to observe and measure the width of the normal adult glottal‐level paraglottic space (PGS). Methods One thousand healthy Han Chinese adults (694 women; 18–79 years) were enrolled between October 2023 and April 2024. PGS ultrasound characteristics were observed, and the width was measured at the midpoint of the anterior, middle, and posterior 1/3 points. The data were stratified by age group and sex. Spearman correlation analysis was used to analyze the correlations between PGS width and sex, age, height, weight, BMI, and BSA. Results The glottic‐level PGS is a triangular hyperechoic structure that is narrow in the front and wide in the back of the parathyroid cartilage section. The PGS width reference ranges (5th and 95th percentiles) were as follows: Male: W 1 (0.45–1.16) mm, W 2 (0.55–1.71) mm, W 3 (1.30–2.35) mm; Female: W 1 (0.55–0.95) mm, W 2 (0.90–1.35) mm, W 3 (1.55–2.00) mm. There were no statistically significant differences in W 1 , W 2 , and W 3 between males and females or between different age groups (all p &gt; 0.05). Conclusions This study summarized normal adult PGS ultrasound characteristics at the glottal level and established references for PGS width, which can provide reference values for clinical practice.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Human Papilloma Virus Does Not Fully Inactivate p53 Cellular Activity in HNSCC</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70085</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70085</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 22:05:04 -0700</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Jovanka Gencel‐Augusto; Hua Li; Liam C. Woerner; Nuo Tian; Ashir A. Borah; Jeffrey N. Myers; Patrick Ha; Daniel E. Johnson; Jennifer R. Grandis</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70085</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70085</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC) is a major global health challenge. Inactivation of the tumor suppressor p53 is the most frequent driver event in this malignancy. p53 inactivation occurs either through TP53 mutations in human papilloma virus (HPV)‐negative cases or via HPV‐mediated p53 degradation in HPV‐positive (HPV+) cases, where most tumors retain a wild‐type (WT) TP53 allele. This underscores the critical role ofp53‐regulated processes in HNSCC pathogenesis. Clinically, HPV+ HNSCC has significantly better outcomes than HPV‐negative disease. However, approximately 10% of HPV+ HNSCC tumors harbor TP53 mutations, suggesting selective pressure to suppress p53 signaling beyond viral degradation. In this study, we demonstrate that HPV+ TP53 ‐WTHNSCC cells have residual, tumor suppressive p53 activity. Clinically, patients with HPV+ TP53 ‐WT tumors exhibit significantly better survival than those with HPV+ TP53 ‐mutantor HPV‐negative tumors. In vitro, WT p53 loss in HPV+ HNSCC cells enhances proliferation, migration, and invasion, and transcriptomic analysis confirms ongoing p53‐dependent gene regulation. HPV+ TP53 ‐WT tumors also display tumor‐suppressive gene methylation patterns, fewer chromosomal alterations, and reduced PI3K‐AKT signaling compared to TP53 ‐mutant HPV+ cases. Notably, p53 loss increases expression of the PI3K catalytic subunit p110α, suppresses the PI3K‐AKT inhibitor INPP5D , and sensitizes cells to pharmacologic PI3Kinhibition. Together, our findings challenge the prevailing view that p53 is completely inactivated in HPV+ HNSCC and reveal tumor suppressive, p53‐driven mechanisms that persist in these tumors. These insights highlight a potential role for TP53 ‐based stratification in guiding treatment decisions and suggest new therapeutic vulnerabilities in HPV+ HNSCC.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Improvement in Thyroid‐Specific Quality of Life After Radio Frequency Ablation of Symptomatic Benign Solitary Thyroid Nodules: A Prospective Cohort Study</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70086</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70086</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 03:01:39 -0700</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Mikkel Kaltoft; Jesper Roed Sorensen; Per Karkov Cramon; Tobias Todsen; Christoffer Holst Hahn</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70086</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70086</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Radio frequency ablation (RFA) is an effective and safe treatment for thyroid nodules, with a volume reduction ratio of 60%–80%. However, only limited reports include validated disease‐specific outcome measures. Using the validated Thyroid‐Related Patient Reported Outcome (ThyPRO), we aimed to investigate changes in disease‐specific quality of life (QOL) following RFA treatment. Methods In this prospective clinical study, we compared ThyPRO questionnaires from baseline and after RFA treatment with a previously collected sample from the general population. Results Fifty‐four patients completed RFA. At baseline, ThyPRO scores were significantly worse than scores from the general population. After treatment, a large and significant improvement was observed on the Goiter Symptoms scale, and moderate improvements were seen on the Cosmetic Complaints and ThyPRO overall QOL scales. At 12 months, patients still had higher scores than the general population on most scales. Conclusion RFA treatment significantly improves goiter‐related symptoms and overall disease‐specific QoL.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Neoadjuvant Immunotherapy for Periauricular Cutaneous Squamous Cell Carcinoma</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70080</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70080</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 05:20:13 -0700</pubDate>
<dc:creator>David Z. Allen; Neil Gross; Marc‐Elie Nader; Renata Ferrarotto; Moran Amit; Priyadharsini Nagarajan; Paul Gidley</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70080</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70080</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background The standard‐of‐care for advanced periauricular cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma (pCSCC) is surgery and adjuvant radiation therapy. Neoadjuvant immunotherapy recently demonstrated high pathologic response rates in patients with resectable pCSCC. Methods This retrospective review was conducted at a tertiary cancer center and included patients with pathologically confirmed pCSCC within the periauricular area treated with curative‐intent surgery with or without neoadjuvant immunotherapy from 2005 to 2025. Patients who received neoadjuvant immunotherapy followed by surgery were age‐ and stage‐matched to those who underwent upfront surgery. The primary outcomes were event‐free survival (EFS) and overall survival (OS), estimated using the Kaplan–Meier method. Results The study included 85 patients. Twenty‐four (28.2%) of whom received neoadjuvant immunotherapy and 61 (71.7%) underwent upfront surgery. The two cohorts had no differences in staging or disease burden at presentation. Forty‐eight patients presented with recurrent disease, equally distributed among the groups (57% vs. 54%, p &gt; 0.05). Patients receiving neoadjuvant immunotherapy had longer median EFS than those undergoing upfront surgery (5.9 vs. 3.4 years; hazard ratio [HR], 0.33; 95% confidence interval [CI], 0.13–0.84; p = 0.02). Specifically, EFS at 2 years was 87% in the neoadjuvant group compared with 55% in the upfront surgery group ( p &lt; 0.05). Median OS was also longer in the neoadjuvant group (not met vs. 4.4 years; HR, 0.32; 95% CI, 0.11–0.90; p = 0.031). Conclusions Neoadjuvant immunotherapy improved survival outcomes in patients with advanced resectable pCSCC. These findings underscore the importance of including this patient population in upcoming randomized trials.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Persistent Opioid Use Following Resection of Oral Cavity Squamous Cell Carcinoma: Incidence and Risk Factors</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70089</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70089</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 05:13:41 -0700</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Cameron C. Lee; Sahil Gandotra; Aaron Bliss; Glyndwr W. Jenkins; Donita Dyalram; Kyle Hatten; Kelly Moyer; Ranee Mehra; Jason Molitoris; Matthew Ferris; Rodney Taylor; Jeffrey S. Wolf; Joshua E. Lubek</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70089</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70089</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Persistent opioid use after head and neck cancer surgery is a growing concern, but data regarding incidence and risk factors remain limited. Methods This retrospective cohort study included patients who underwent primary resection of oral cavity squamous cell carcinoma between 2016 and 2022. Preoperative opioid use was classified as naïve, intermittent, or chronic using prescription drug monitoring data. Persistent use was defined as filling an opioid prescription attributed to surgery and two consecutive prescriptions between 120 and 365 days postoperatively. Regression analysis identified independent predictors. Results Among 430 subjects, 18.8% met criteria for persistent opioid use. Chronic preoperative use ( p = 0.008), G‐tube persistence at 12 months ( p = 0.041), chronic pain diagnosis ( p = 0.036), and cancer recurrence ( p = 0.021) were independent predictors. Persistent use peaked between 120 and 180 days postoperatively. Conclusion Persistent opioid use is common after oral cancer resection and is strongly associated with preoperative opioid use. Early risk stratification may improve outcomes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Exploring Transitions in Care Among Patients With Head and Neck Cancer: A Scoping Review</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70061</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70061</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 02:30:48 -0700</pubDate>
<dc:creator>L. Fillo; A. Hezam; J. Kersen; S. Kurbatfinski; A. Thomas; S. Ibadin; D. L. Lorenzetti; S. P. Chandarana; J. C. Dort; K. M. Sauro</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70061</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70061</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Individuals living with and beyond head and neck cancer (HNC) experience many transitions in care (TiC), as their treatment and care involve a team of multidisciplinary healthcare providers across a variety of settings. TiC can be associated with medical error, patient dissatisfaction with care, and overuse of healthcare resources. The objective of this study is to understand TiC among individuals living with and beyond HNC by mapping and characterizing the existing evidence. Methods This scoping review identified evidence sources describing TiC among individuals living with and beyond HNC by searching five medical research databases using structured language and keywords related to the population (cancer) and concept (TiC). Titles and abstracts, and full texts were screened in duplicate for eligibility. Eligible studies were those that described or evaluated TiC among individuals with HNC, of any study design published in any language without restriction based on the date of publication. Quantitative data were summarized using descriptive statistics, and qualitative data were synthesized using thematic analysis. Results The search identified 26,431 unique evidence sources, of which 3375 were screened in full‐text, and 57 were included. Most studies were conducted in the United States between 2001 and 2024 and were retrospective cohort studies. Included evidence sources most frequently focused on the delays in the transition from diagnosis to treatment, followed by the TiC from surgery to radiation. The majority of evidence sources reported system‐level outcomes followed by patient‐level outcomes. Eight evidence sources described interventions to improve TiC. Conclusion The study identified a gap in our evidence regarding transitions during active treatment and in evaluating interventions to improve TiC among individuals living with and beyond HNC. Future research should focus on bridging these gaps to improve TiC and consequently outcomes for individuals living with and beyond HNC.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Oncologic Safety of Facial‐Vessel–Based Buccinator Myomucosal Flaps for Tongue and Oral Floor Reconstruction: A Retrospective Multicenter Case–Control Study</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70082</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70082</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 02:09:53 -0700</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Luigi Angelo Vaira; Olindo Massarelli; Jerry Polesel; Andrea Ferri; Carlos M. Chiesa‐Estomba; Ignacio Navarro Cuéllar; Giuseppe Consorti; Giulio Cirignaco; Marco Cucurullo; Giovanni Salzano; Sourabh Padmanabhan; Abhijith George; Marzia Petrocelli; Javeria Ali; Jose A. González‐Garcia; Alfonso Manfuso; Tareck Ayad; Carlos Navarro Cuéllar; Fabiola Giudici; Jerome R. Lechien; Shawn T. Joseph; Chiara Copelli; Federico Biglioli; Silvano Ferrari; Giacomo De Riu</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70082</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70082</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Buccinator myomucosal flaps (BMFs) have been proposed as a reconstructive solution for defects of the tongue and oral floor; however, their harvest requires preservation of the facial artery and vein. This study aimed to evaluate the oncologic safety of this approach compared with free fasciocutaneous flaps (FFF). Methods A retrospective multicenter case–control study including cT1–T3 cN0 tongue/oral floor squamous cell carcinoma was performed. Cases received BMFs while controls received FFFs. The primary endpoint was progression‐free survival (PFS) tested for non‐inferiority. Secondary endpoints were overall survival (OS), disease‐specific survival (DSS), and cumulative incidence of local, regional, and distant recurrence using competing‐risk methods. Results A total of 615 patients (BMF n = 390; FFF n = 225) with comparable baselines were included. Five‐year PFS was 69.8% (BMF) versus 66.2% (FFF); adjusted HR (FFF vs. BMF) 0.87 (95% CI: 0.43–1.78), meeting non‐inferiority. Five‐year OS was 77.9% versus 73.5%. Cumulative incidence of recurrence was similar: local 7.5% versus 8.3%, regional 6.3% versus 6.1%, and distant 2.1% versus 1.7%. Conclusions Preservation of the facial artery and vein during selective neck dissection did not compromise oncologic outcomes. Facial‐vessel–based BMFs are a valid option for small‐to‐medium tongue/oral floor defects in appropriately selected cN0 patients when meticulous level I clearance is performed and a pull‐through resection is not required.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Vocal Fold Immobility After Radiofrequency Ablation of Thyroid Nodules: A Survey of Laryngologists and an Algorithm for Periprocedural Voice Assessment</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70081</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70081</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 01:17:11 -0700</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Vaninder Kaur Dhillon; Catherine Fiona Sinclair</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70081</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70081</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Rates of vocal fold motion impairment (VFMI) during and after thermal ablative treatments for thyroid nodules have not been well documented. This study surveys a large group of laryngologists to assess the rate of VFMI and dysphonia referral patterns after thermal ablation. A peri‐procedural voice assessment algorithm for proceduralists performing thermal ablation for thyroid nodules is presented. Methods Thirteen‐question‐survey related to VFMI postablation. Results Sixty‐one respondents completed the survey. One‐third of total respondents affirmed a VFMI after thermal ablation, with 81% documenting evidence on laryngeal examination. Immediate dysphonia was the most common presenting symptom. Referral patterns varied, but a large portion of patients were referred more than one week postprocedure despite the proceduralist having knowledge of potential VFMI. Conclusion VFMI is a risk during thermal ablation of thyroid nodules. Greater attention to voice during ablation and use of a procedural voice assessment algorithm may mitigate the risk of injury and potentially improve outcomes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Occurrence, Risk Factors, and Early Clinical Outcomes of Dysphagia on Postoperative Day 7 in Patients With Oral Cancer Undergoing Free‐Flap Reconstruction Surgery: A Hospital‐Based Retrospective Study</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70075</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70075</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:30:44 -0700</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Wen‐Chuan Hsu; Wen‐Pin Yu; Hui‐Mei Han; Huang‐Kai Kao; Hsiao‐Yean Chiu</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70075</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70075</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Dysphagia is common in patients with oral cancer undergoing flap reconstruction surgery. Surgical resection and reconstruction can affect the sensory and motor functions associated with swallowing. Studies on dysphagia have not investigated patients with oral cancer undergoing flap reconstruction surgery. In this hospital‐based retrospective study, we examined the occurrence rates, risk factors, and clinical outcomes of dysphagia in patients with oral cancer undergoing flap reconstruction surgery. Methods Data were collected from the Chang Gung Research Database, which includes structured and unstructured electronic medical records. These data covered the period from January 1 to November 30, 2022. A total of 892 patients were included in the study. Dysphagia was identified on the basis of NANDA International Nursing Diagnoses criteria. Univariate and multivariable logistic regression models were used for data analysis. Results Of a total of 892 patients, 679 (76.1%) experienced dysphagia. Body mass index, smoking status, alcohol consumption, betel nut chewing, pain score, neck lymph node dissection, radiotherapy, and chemotherapy were identified as significant risk factors for dysphagia. Compared with those without dysphagia, patients with dysphagia had significantly higher rates of nasogastric tube placement and tracheostomy at discharge, longer hospital stays, and higher readmission rates. Conclusions Dysphagia is common in patients with oral cancer undergoing flap reconstruction surgery and is associated with certain risk factors and clinical outcomes. Enhancing postoperative care and implementing targeted interventions can facilitate the development of precise treatment plans aimed at reducing the incidence of dysphagia and improving the overall quality of care for patients undergoing flap reconstruction surgery.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Loss of the Y Chromosome in Oral Potentially Premalignant Disorders Predicts Malignant Progression: An Integrative Cross‐Species Multi‐Cohort Bioinformatic Study</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70070</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70070</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 02:06:20 -0700</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Rui Han; Jos B. Poell; Cristina Conde‐Lopez; Tuula Salo; Ina Kurth; Ruud H. Brakenhoff; Jochen Hess</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70070</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70070</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background The loss of the Y chromosome (LOY) and the extreme down‐regulation of Y chromosome gene expression (EDY) are frequently observed in oral squamous cell carcinoma (OSCC). However, their roles in oral potentially malignant disorders (OPMDs) are unclear. Methods A comprehensive bioinformatic analysis was performed using publicly available datasets from chemically induced mouse OSCC models and human cohorts. The analysis included LOY/EDY detection, gene set variation analysis (GSVA), PROGENy pathway profiling, cell‐to‐cell communication inference, and epigenetic correlation studies. Results LOY was prevalent among men with OPMD, and EDY was identified in both mouse models and human OPMDs. The presence of LOY/EDY was associated with a higher risk of OPMD progression to OSCC. Single‐cell analysis revealed that EDY‐positive epithelial cells exhibited elevated oncogenic pathway activity and enhanced IL17‐IL17RC signaling, possibly due to the loss of KDM5D in epithelial cells and altered epigenetic regulation. Conclusions LOY/EDY can be detected in OPMD and promotes malignant progression by altering oncogenic signaling and epithelial cell interactions. LOY/EDY may serve as both a diagnostic biomarker and a therapeutic target, improving clinical management and patient outcomes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Proton Therapy for Paranasal Sinus Cancer: Clinical Outcomes and Patterns of Failure</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70078</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70078</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 21:47:39 -0700</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Caineng Cao; Teeradon Treechairusame; Nadeem Riaz; Sean M. McBride; Daphna Y. Gelblum; Achraf Shamseddine; Marc A. Cohen; Richard J. Wong; Jennifer R. Cracchiolo; Ian Ganly; Eric J. Sherman; Alan L. Ho; Winston Wong; Lara A. Dunn; Nancy Y. Lee</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70078</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70078</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Purpose To evaluate the clinical outcomes and patterns of failure in patients with paranasal sinus cancer treated by proton therapy during 2013–2022. Methods and Materials This retrospective study included 88 patients with newly diagnosed nonmetastatic paranasal sinus cancer treated by proton therapy at a tertiary academic cancer center from August 2013 to November 2022. Fifteen patients were treated by three‐dimensional conformal proton technique ( 3DCPT ) and 73 patients were treated by intensity modulated proton therapy ( IMPT ). The main outcomes were the long‐term toxicity, patterns of failure and survival outcomes, including cumulative incidence of local or regional failures ( LRF ) and overall survival ( OS ). Results The median (interquartile range [ IQR ]) follow‐up time for the overall group was 57.3 (38.5–82.6) months. Acute grade 3 radiation dermatitis and late grade 3 nasal congestion occurred significantly more frequently in the 3DCPT group compared to the IMPT group (20.0% vs. 4.1%, p = 0.008; 33.3% vs. 5.6%, p = 0.004, respectively). By the last follow‐up, 33 patients had developed treatment failures. A total of 21 patients (23.9%) developed local failures, 14 were considered in‐field failure; 4 were marginal; 3 were out‐of‐field failure. The 5y‐cumulative incidence of LRF and OS rate of the overall group were 25% [95% confidence interval ( CI ), 16–35] and 79.4% (70.2–89.8), respectively. There were no statistically significant differences following 3DCPT and IMPT in cumulative incidence of LRF and OS . Conclusions Proton therapy yielded excellent therapeutic outcomes in the management of paranasal sinus cancer. IMPT holds significant potential in enhancing the therapeutic ratio in paranasal sinus cancer and warrants further exploration in clinical settings.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>A Practical Method for Detecting Prognostic CD57+ T Cells in Head and Neck Cancer</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70074</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70074</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 18:24:53 -0700</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Brianna Brammer; Brendan L. C. Kinney; Vikash Kansal; Nicole C. Schmitt</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70074</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70074</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Recurrence of head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC) affects nearly half of patients and greatly reduces survival. There are currently no well‐established mechanisms to predict which HNSCC patients will experience disease recurrence. We have previously shown that an elevated proportion of highly differentiated, CD57+ effector memory T (HD TEMRA) cells in circulation is associated with early recurrence and poor locoregional disease control in HNSCC patients. Methods Here, we present refined flow cytometry panels utilizing fewer fluorescent antibodies that retain the prognostic value of HD TEMRA cells in predicting HNSCC recurrence. Results In our cohort of surgically treated HNSCC patients, identifying HD TEMRA cells via flow cytometry as live CD8+ CD28− CD57+ cells effectively predicted disease recurrence. When assessing this cohort by disease subsite, we found that for patients with oral squamous cell carcinoma, identifying HD TEMRA cells by CD8+ CD57+ alone was sufficient for predicting locoregional disease recurrence. Conclusions These refined panels enhance the clinical utility of HD TEMRA proportion as a biomarker due to their technical and analytic ease. Implementation of HD TEMRA cell proportion as a clinical biomarker could aid in personalized HNSCC treatment planning.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>A Real‐World Phase IV Superiority Trial and Cost‐Effectiveness Analysis of the Addition of Low‐Dose Nivolumab to Triple Metronomic Chemotherapy Compared to the Paclitaxel Carboplatin Regimen in Recurrent or Metastatic Head and Neck Cancer Patients</title>
<link>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70077</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.70077</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 02:28:28 -0700</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Avinash Khadela; Rajsi Parikh; Jaydeep Vaghela; Yatra Chauhan; Vraj B. Shah; Rushabh Kothari; Manthan Merja</dc:creator>
<prism:publicationName>Head &amp;amp; Neck</prism:publicationName>
<prism:doi>10.1002/hed.70077</prism:doi>
<description>Journal: Head &amp;amp; Neck | DOI: 10.1002/hed.70077</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>ABSTRACT Background Limited data are available regarding the comparison of low‐dose immunotherapy when added to oral metronomic chemotherapy with conventional induction chemotherapy regimens in recurrent/metastatic Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma (R/M HNSCC). Methods This real‐world phase IV superiority trial recruited adult patients with R/M HNSCC being treated with palliative intent. Patients were assigned to TMC‐I or PC. The primary endpoints were median OS, PFS, ORR, and ICER, and the safety assessment was the secondary endpoint. Results A total of 154 patients were recruited: 78 in the TMC‐I arm and 76 in the PC arm. The median OS was 15.13 months (95% CI, 11.05–19.20) versus 9.8 months (95% CI, 7.50–12.09) ( p &lt; 0.01), and the median PFS was 11.20 months (95% CI, 5.43–16.96) versus 7.41 months (95% CI, 6.73–8.08) ( p &lt; 0.01) for the TMC‐I and PC arms, respectively. The ORR was 69.23% for TMC‐I and 31.57% for the PC arm, respectively. The ICER between both arms was 68 947. Conclusion A significant improvement in survival, tolerability, and reasonable cost‐effectiveness was observed with low‐dose immunotherapy when added to oral metronomic chemotherapy compared to conventional chemotherapy regimens.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>