<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Head &amp; Neck Cancer – Curated Journal Feed</title>
<link>https://colmmemedsurv.github.io/sentinelnode/</link>
<description>Automatically curated from selected journal RSS feeds. Metadata is copied only when present in the source feed.</description>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2025 22:08:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
<item>
<title>Merkel-Cell Carcinoma</title>
<link>https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMicm2513302?rss=searchAndBrowse</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMicm2513302?rss=searchAndBrowse</guid>
<pubDate>2025-12-18</pubDate>
<description>Journal: The New England Journal of Medicine: Search Results in Hematology/Oncology
DOI: 10.1056/NEJMicm2513302
Authors: Zunaid Ahmed, Willem Visser


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
A 72-year-old woman presented with a 3.5-month history of an enlarging, painless lump on her cheek. Examination showed a dome-shaped, reddish nodule on the left cheek, with a shiny surface and central hemorrhagic crust.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>[Correspondence] Misclassification of p16-positive, HPV-negative patients biases de-escalation trials</title>
<link>https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lanonc/article/PIIS1470-2045(25)00616-3/fulltext?rss=yes</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lanonc/article/PIIS1470-2045(25)00616-3/fulltext?rss=yes</guid>
<pubDate>2025-12</pubDate>
<description>Journal: The Lancet Oncology
DOI: 10.1016/S1470-2045(25)00616-3
Authors: Jessica T Lovett, Michael T Wotman, Marshall Posner


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
We read with interest the Article by Daniel Ma and colleagues in The Lancet Oncology.1 Ma and colleagues should be congratulated on completing a randomised trial of de-escalated radiotherapy in patients with p16-positive oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma. The authors report progression-free survival, local regional control, freedom from distant metastases, and overall survival as secondary endpoints. The de-escalation protocol resulted in a reduction in progression-free survival, local regional control, and systemic control in patients who received de-escalated treatment with extracapsular extension compared with patients who received standard of care.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>[Correspondence] Misclassification of p16-positive, HPV-negative patients biases de-escalation trials – Authors&apos; reply</title>
<link>https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lanonc/article/PIIS1470-2045(25)00655-2/fulltext?rss=yes</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lanonc/article/PIIS1470-2045(25)00655-2/fulltext?rss=yes</guid>
<pubDate>2025-12</pubDate>
<description>Journal: The Lancet Oncology
DOI: 10.1016/S1470-2045(25)00655-2
Authors: David M Routman, James S Lewis, Daniel J Ma


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
We appreciate the important points raised by Jessica T Lovett and colleagues regarding p16 immunohistochemistry as a surrogate for HPV status in oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma in de-escalation studies such as MC1675.1 As they noted, the prognostic implications of p16 and HPV discordance have been previously analysed, such as in a multinational study by Mehanna and colleagues.2 Patients who were p16-positive and HPV-negative had an increased rate of cancer recurrence (hazard ratio 1·92, 95% CI 1·42–2·60).</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Unexpected Results of Induction Chemotherapy vs Adjuvant Chemotherapy</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaoncology/fullarticle/2840005</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaoncology/fullarticle/2840005</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Oncology Current Issue
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoncol.2025.4092


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
To the Editor We read with interest the results of the phase 3 randomized clinical trial by Guo et al that investigated the important question if induction chemotherapy (IC) was superior to adjuvant chemotherapy (AC) when added to a backbone of concurrent chemoradiotherapy (CCRT) in patients with N2-3 nasopharyngeal carcinoma (NPC). For IC, the investigators used the triplet combination of paclitaxel-cisplatin-fluorouracil (TPF), whereas doublet cisplatin-fluorouracil (PF) was used for AC. The trial was powered to detect a 12% difference in progression-free survival (PFS) in favor of IC, and enrolled 324 patients, with 162 patients in each group. However, this was a negative trial with comparable 3-year PFS between IC plus CCRT and CCRT plus AC, contrasting the results of the NPC-0501 trial by the Hong Kong NPC study group, which showed an improvement for PFS in favor of IC, albeit subtle differences exist between both trials. Intriguingly, in the present study, IC was associated with poorer local control compared with AC.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Mind, Machine, and Medicine</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2840474</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2840474</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Current Issue
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4108


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
This Viewpoint summarizes the presidential address of the president of the American Head and Neck Society.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Multiomic Selection of Cancer-Testis Antigens as Precision Immuno-oncologic Targets in Head and Neck Cancer</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2840416</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2840416</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Current Issue
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.3563


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
This cross-sectional study evaluates specific cancer-testis antigens as potential precision immuno-oncologic targets in both previously untreated (de novo) and recurrent head and neck squamous cell carcinoma tumors.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Are We Training Too Many Head and Neck Fellows?</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2840414</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2840414</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Current Issue
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.3471


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
This Viewpoint discusses the purpose of head and neck fellowship and what the correct number of practicing head and neck surgeons is.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Reimbursement for Thyroid Surgery and Potential Solutions</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2840186</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2840186</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Current Issue
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.3696


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
This economic evaluation characterizes trends in Medicare reimbursement for thyroid surgery and provides evidence for future discussions on payment reforms.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Contralateral Tonsil in p16-Positive Tonsil Squamous Cell Carcinoma</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2840185</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2840185</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Current Issue
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2410


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
This Viewpoint examines current surgical guidelines and emerging evidence regarding the optimal treatment of patients with p16-positive oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Improving Palliative Care for Patients With Head and Neck Cancer</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2838819</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2838819</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Current Issue
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2688


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
In this issue of JAMA Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery, Fu et al used data from the Ontario Cancer Registry to evaluate palliative care (PC) use in 11 135 patients with head and neck cancer (HNC) during their last year of life. They found that PC was utilized in 90% of patients and was associated with increased monthly costs at the end of life, a greater number of emergency department visits and hospital admissions, and a lower likelihood of dying at home compared to non-PC recipients. The majority of PC was received in the inpatient setting and was initiated in the last 6 months of life. Gastrostomy and/or tracheostomy tube placement occurred in 11% of patients in the last year of life and was associated with increased costs that were partially mitigated by early (&amp;amp;gt;6 months before death) PC involvement. The authors conclude that early PC involvement may attenuate the costs associated with tracheostomy and gastrostomy tube use in the last year of life but that it does not reduce the use of aggressive hospital-based care or facilitate home deaths. These findings highlight the high symptom burden associated with HNC end-of-life care and demonstrate gaps in the current delivery of PC to this population.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Palliative Care With Tube Use and End-of-Life Quality and Costs in Head and Neck Cancer</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2838814</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2838814</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Current Issue
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2687


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
This cohort study assesses the association of palliative care and tracheostomy or gastrostomy tubes with end-of-life costs among patients with head and neck cancer during the last year of life.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Barriers and Timely Postoperative Radiation Therapy in Head and Neck Cancer</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2838772</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2838772</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Current Issue
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2824


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
This cohort study investigates potential barriers to timely postoperative radiation therapy, defined as initiating radiation care within 6 weeks of surgery.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Preexisting Psychiatric Risk Factors and Any and Long-Term Opioid Use in Head and Neck Cancer</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2838194</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2838194</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Current Issue
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2649


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
This cohort study evaluates whether preexisting psychiatric risk factors are associated with any opioid prescriptions and long-term opioid therapy in patients with head and neck cancer.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Unilateral vs Bilateral Transoral Surgery for Tonsil SCCa</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2837623</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2837623</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Current Issue
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2235


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
This systematic review and meta-analysis assesses the second primary tumor rates, oncologic survival, functional outcomes, and complications between bilateral and unilateral transoral surgery for tonsillar squamous cell carcinoma (SCCa).</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Emerging Role of Pathologic Response in Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma Immunotherapy</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2837004</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2837004</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Current Issue
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.2111


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
Immune checkpoint inhibitors (ICIs) have transformed the treatment of recurrent and metastatic head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC), but combination studies in the definitive disease setting with concurrent chemoradiation have been disappointing. New results from the KEYNOTE-689 phase 3 trial suggest the addition of neoadjuvant followed by adjuvant pembrolizumab in the perioperative setting may represent a new standard of care for resectable locally advanced HNSCC. Pembrolizumab improved event-free survival (EFS) by a median of 21.4 months compared to standard therapy. This trial also established safety in the surgical setting; similar proportions of patients in both the treatment and control arms successfully completed surgery. These findings may transform the treatment landscape of resectable locally advanced HNSCC, where current 3-year progression-free survival remains between 49% and 64%. While the contribution of components, neoadjuvant and/or adjuvant, in KEYNOTE-689 remains undefined, identifying which patients are most likely to benefit from ICI therapy in the definitive setting is an important goal.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Pathologic Treatment Effect and Survival in HPV-Negative HNSCC Following Neoadjuvant Nivolumab</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2837002</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2837002</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Current Issue
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1707


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
This cohort study sets out to establish a clinically significant pathologic treatment effect threshold to define pathologic responders and assess related survival outcomes in patients with head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC) undergoing neoadjuvant treatment with immune checkpoint inhibitors.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Patients With Head and Neck Cancer and High Health Care Costs</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2836569</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2836569</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Current Issue
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1976


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
This population-based, retrospective cohort study characterizes patients with head and neck cancer whose care was associated with the highest health care costs during their first year after diagnosis compared with patients with low or medium care costs.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Unilateral vs Bilateral Transoral Robotic Surgery for HPV-Positive Tonsillar Squamous Cell Carcinoma</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2836483</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2836483</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Current Issue
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1833


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
This cohort study assesses postoperative complications, functional outcomes, contralateral tonsil second primary rates, and survival between unilateral and bilateral transoral robotic surgery for tonsillar human papillomavirus (HPV)–related oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Considerations and Cautions in Postoperative Circulating Tumor HPV DNA Kinetics</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2834216</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2834216</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Current Issue
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1612


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
Human papillomavirus (HPV)–associated oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma (OPSCC) is a rapidly evolving field in which HPV circulating tumor  DNA (ctDNA) has emerged as a promising biomarker for cancer response and minimal residual disease (MRD) detection. In a study published in JAMA Otolaryngology-Head &amp;amp;amp; Neck Surgery, Yin et al investigate the kinetics of postoperative HPV ctDNA in a cohort of patients undergoing primary surgery for HPV-OPSCC. In this prospective study of 84 patients, 57 (82.6%) had detectable pretreatment samples. Of those, 35 patients had blood draws at both specified time points: postoperative day (POD) 1 to 2 and postoperative week (POW) 2. Similar to previous studies, these data support a correlation between preoperative HPV ctDNA levels and tumor stage, size of nodal disease, and presence of extranodal extension. The crux of this recent work, however, focuses on the positive and negative predictive values in addition to specific timing considerations of postoperative circulating tumor DNA detectability. Of 35 patients with complete blood draws, 16 (45.7%) remained detectable at POD 1 to 2; however of these, only 3 continued to be detectable at POW 2. These data yield a negative predictive value of 95% (95% CI, 74%-100%) and a positive predictive value of 19% (95% CI, 4%-46%), highlighting the superior reliability of the 2-week time point for MRD assessment. The authors propose an algorithm whereby patients with detectable samples on POD 1 to 2 undergo repeat testing at POW 2 if being used to guide adjuvant decisions. This 2-step approach balances timely risk stratification with avoidance of overtreatment, recognizing that adjuvant therapy planning requires a lead time of up to 6 weeks for multidisciplinary coordination. Of note, use of MRD for adjuvant decisions is currently restricted to clinical trials as this is not yet standard of care.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Postoperative ctHPVDNA Kinetics in Patients With HPV-Related Oropharyngeal Cancer</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2834215</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2834215</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Current Issue
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.1606


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
This cohort study investigates the early postoperative kinetics of circulating tumor human papillomavirus DNA (ctHPVDNA) in patients with HPV-associated oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Efficacy of a Brief Cognitive Behavioral Treatment Across Body Image Distress Domains</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2833816</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2833816</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Current Issue
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.0965


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
This secondary analysis of a randomized clinical trial evaluates whether a brief, tailored cognitive behavioral treatment program is effective across multiple domains of head and neck cancer–related body image distress.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Pathologic Response and Survival After Neoadjuvant Immunotherapy for HNSCC</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2842514</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2842514</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Online First
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4573


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
This systematic review and meta-analysis assesses the association between achievement of a pathologic treatment response and improvement in disease-free survival in head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC).</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Thyroid Lobectomy and Neck Dissection for N1b Papillary Thyroid Carcinoma</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2842513</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2842513</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Online First
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4653


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
This cohort study examines recurrence and survival outcomes in propensity-matched thyroid lobectomy vs total thyroidectomy + radioactive iodine patients who presented with ipsilateral N1b papillary thyroid carcinoma.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Pembrolizumab in Head and Neck Cancer—Promise and Price</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2842512</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2842512</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Online First
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4624


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
This Viewpoint considers the financial impact of expanding the indication of pembrolizumab for treatment of resectable locally advanced head and neck squamous cell carcinoma expressing programmed cell death 1 ligand 1.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Factors Associated With Opioid Refills After Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery</title>
<link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2842391</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamaotolaryngology/fullarticle/2842391</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Journal: JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp;amp; Neck Surgery Online First
DOI: 10.1001/jamaoto.2025.4576


Abstract/summary (from RSS):
This cohort study examines perioperative risk factors associated with opioid refill prescriptions within 90 days after discharge among adults patients who underwent otolaryngology–head and neck surgery procedures.</description>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>